<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Salvation in a mystery: or A prospective glasse for Englands case. As it was laid forth in a sermon preached at Margarets in Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons, at their monthly fast, March 27. 1644. / By John Bond, B.LL. late lecturer in the city of Exceter, now preacher at the Savoy in London. A member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of the Commons House.</title>
            <author>Bond, John, 1612-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E43_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1754</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860213</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860213</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77007)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E43[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Salvation in a mystery: or A prospective glasse for Englands case. As it was laid forth in a sermon preached at Margarets in Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons, at their monthly fast, March 27. 1644. / By John Bond, B.LL. late lecturer in the city of Exceter, now preacher at the Savoy in London. A member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of the Commons House.</title>
                  <author>Bond, John, 1612-1676.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L.N. for Francis Eglesfeild, and are to be sold at the signe of the Marygold in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf bears an order to print.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at a late fast, before the Honourable House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XLV, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:112329:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Mercurii,</hi> 27 <hi>Martii,</hi> 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day ordered by the Commons, Aſſembled in Parliament, That Maſter BOND, and Maſter NICOLLS. do from this Howſe give Thanks unto Maſter BOND, for his great pains he tooke in the Sermon he preached this day at MARGRET WESTMIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER at the intreaty of this Houſe (it being the day of Publike Humiliation) And they are to deſire him to print his Sermon. And it is Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that none preſume to print or reprent his Sermon without being authoriſed vnder the hand wrighting of the ſaid Maſter BOND.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>I do appoint <hi>Francis Eglesfeild</hi> to Print my Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Bond.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112329:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SALVATION IN A MYSTERY: Or A PROSPECTIVE GLASSE for ENGLANDS Caſe.</p>
            <p>As it was laid forth in a Sermon preached at MARGARETS in Weſtminſter, before the Honourable Houſe of Commons, at their monthly <hi>Faſt,</hi> March 27. 1644.</p>
            <p>BY JOHN BOND, B. LL. late Lecturer in the City of Exceter, now Preacher at the <hi>Savoy</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Member of the Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order of the Commons Houſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EXOD. 3. v. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Buſh burned with fire, and the Buſh was not conſumed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JUDG. 14. v. 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Out of the eater came forth meat, and out of the ſtrong came forth ſweetneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>L. N.</hi> for <hi>Francis Eglesfeild,</hi> and are to be ſold at the figne of the Marygold in Pauls Church-yard. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:112329:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112329:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE HOUSE OF COMMONS NOW ASSEMBLED IN PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>HONOURABLE WORTHIES:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT which by your firſt command, was in part, preſented to your eares from the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> is here at your ſecond command, fully repreſented to your eyes from the <hi>Preſſe.</hi> It is a piece, I dare ſay, as rare and <hi>uſefull</hi> for the Plot and <hi>Subject,</hi> which are immediatly the <hi>Lords;</hi> as it is plaine and <hi>homely</hi> in <hi>my</hi> ſtile and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod:</hi> In the dreſſe thereof, I thought it a duty to <hi>put off Ornaments;</hi> for although it was Preached upon the yeerly day of the <hi>Kings Inauguration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">March 27.</note> yet that ſeaſon was alſo the Monthly day of the <hi>Kingdoms Humiliation;</hi> when you did endeavour to Weepe, Pray, and Faſt for the <hi>Royall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie;</hi> whilſt others (perhaps at <hi>Oxford</hi>) did Drinke, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme,
<pb facs="tcp:112329:3"/>and Debauch themſelves, to ſhew their <hi>Loyaltie</hi> to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſubject</hi> of this ſermon, is like the <hi>two Pillars</hi> which guided (our type) Iſrael through the Wilderneſſe to <hi>Canaan</hi> by day, and night: The one was a <hi>Cloude,</hi> which might well ſignifie the <hi>Lord hiding himſelfe:</hi> The other of <hi>Fire,</hi> importing him to be <hi>the Saviour of Iſrael</hi> even whilſt he was in that Cloude.</p>
            <p>There is much talke now a dayes of <hi>now light,</hi> and that new light as it is held forth by ſome, is nothing leſſe then <hi>old dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> I may ſafely promiſe you in this Treatiſe, at leaſt, the <hi>dawning of</hi> a light that is <hi>new Orthodoxe</hi> and <hi>certaine:</hi> By which I have endavoured to begin the diſcovery of a hidden <hi>Mine</hi> of precious <hi>Providence;</hi> though all my labours, have ſcarcely opened the uppermoſt ſurface of the ground. I ſhall leave the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate ſearching of the <hi>veynes</hi> to more able <hi>obſervers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe that I did make an <hi>Eſſay</hi> upon his very Text, in my <hi>native climate,</hi> before my baniſhment; but being <hi>plundered</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſpeculative</hi> thoughts; and having, ſince that time in ſome meaſure <hi>experimented</hi> this text; I conceive my ſelfe <hi>bound</hi> in conſcience to give you ſome <hi>meate out of my Eater.</hi> Surely there is a vaſt difference betweene <hi>hearing</hi> of the Lord <hi>by the hearing of the eare</hi> and when <hi>our eyes have ſeene him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 42.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>May it pleaſe you therefore to <hi>travell</hi> over this unuſuall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>once againe;</hi> becauſe <hi>Myſteries</hi> commonly are not underſtood at the <hi>firſt</hi> peruſall. Sure I am that never any Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> had greater need of <hi>Viatica</hi> than your ſelves: You are <hi>made</hi> a <hi>Spectacle to Angels and Men;</hi> And beleeve it, you are <hi>ſet</hi> up, <hi>for the fall and riſing againe of many in</hi> England. The Lord hath <hi>cut off</hi> all <hi>bridges</hi> behind you (and bleſſed be his name that they are cut off) And now, together with you, all the Treaſures of <hi>great Britaine</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are <hi>imbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued:</hi> And according to your <hi>ſtanding</hi> or <hi>falling</hi> in this great Cauſe, muſt the preſent Generation and their Poſterities in the three Kingdoms, <hi>begin</hi> the <hi>dates</hi> of their perpetuall weal or woe; for, pure <hi>Reformation,</hi> or open <hi>Popery;</hi> ingenious <hi>Liberty,</hi> or Norman <hi>Slavery</hi> muſt now be made the ſettled Master: Nay,
<pb facs="tcp:112329:3"/>to allude to <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſpeech, you do <hi>now carry the whole Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cauſe, withall its Fortunes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For mine <hi>owne part,</hi> there is nothing upon earth, that doth more amaze mine intellectualls, then the <hi>prodigious Lethargie</hi> that doth ſtill reſt upon the heads and hearts of curſed <hi>Neuters,</hi> and Proteſtant <hi>Malignants</hi> in the Land, even now when <hi>both parties</hi> do abhor indifferency, and that the excreable <hi>Rebels of Ireland</hi> are brought over: But I might ſilence my ſelfe in this <hi>Quos perdece vult Jupiter, cos dementat.</hi> Surely the Lord hath ſmitten the generallity of the Land <hi>with madneſſe and blindneſſe and aſtoniſhment of heart,</hi> as he threatned the Iews.
<note place="margin">Deut. 28.28</note> Otherwiſe they could never <hi>dreame</hi> of <hi>defending Parliaments</hi> by <hi>Malefactors, Property</hi> by <hi>Deſperado's,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtaniſme</hi> by <hi>Iriſh Rebels.</hi> May, we not fear leſt the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> or <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or other <hi>Forreigners,</hi> may <hi>beg</hi> the whole Land of the King, and obtaine it, alleadging that the Nation, is not <hi>Compos mentis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my hope ſhall be, that after the Lord hath <hi>deeply hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> us for our old and new abominations,
<note place="margin">Dan. 4.14.</note> and broken us as he did <hi>Nebuchadnezzer,</hi> when he hath <hi>hewen us downe, cut off our branches, ſhaken off our leaves, and ſcattered our fruits;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 25.</note> when he hath <hi>driven us from men,</hi> and ſuffered our <hi>haires to grow like Eagles feathers, and our nayles like Birds clawes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 33.</note> then at the <hi>end of the dayes,</hi> mens <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi> ſhall <hi>returne to them againe,</hi> and perhaps, our glory alſo. At leaſt, I am confident,
<note place="margin">Zeph. 3.12.</note> that God will <hi>leave in the middeſt of us an afflicted and poore people, and they ſhall truſt in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Meane while, it is my <hi>Petition to you,</hi> and <hi>for</hi> you (worthy Patriots) that you may <hi>hold-out</hi> through all thoſe ſeas of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties which are before you;
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.10.</note> And that you may remember that <hi>God is not unrighteous to forget your worke and labour of love, which you have ſhewed toward his name:</hi> Yea,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.3.</note> you may take it for a poſitive promiſe. <hi>The Lord is faithfull, who ſhall ſtabliſh you, and keepe you from evill;
<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> and we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the Lord, touching you, that you both do, and will
<pb facs="tcp:112329:4"/>do, the things which he commands you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>And the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and into the patient wayting for Chriſt.</hi> This is the fixed hope, and ſhall ever be the fervent prayer, of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Study at the Savoy <date>April <hi>20. 1644.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Humble and willing Servant, <hi>JOHN BOND.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112329:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED at a late Faſt before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH 45.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Verily, Thou art a God that hideſt Thy ſelfe, O God of Iſrael the Saviour.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Spring-head</hi> of this Text (as ſome conceive) doth ariſe at the ſixth verſe of the 44.
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Analyſis.</note> Chapter. Others doe fetch it as high as chap. 43. verſ. 14. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, the Holy One of Iſrael; for your ſakes I have ſent to Babylon,</hi> &amp;c. And the <hi>Streames</hi> do run downe as far as the end of chap. 48. The <hi>whole</hi> divides it ſelfe into <hi>two branches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>a propheticall promiſe</hi> of the returne of the Jewes from their Babyloniſh captivity: That ends with this chapter of my Text. And,</p>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>a Propheticall threatning</hi> of the downfall of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhortly after that deliverance: This extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the beginning of the next Chapter <hi>[Bel boweth downe, Nebo ſtoopeth]</hi> to the end of this Propheſie, chapt. 48. <hi>[There is no peace, ſaith the Lord, unto the wicked.]</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112329:5"/>
            <p>In this propheticall-promiſory-Chapter of my Text,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Coherence.</note> commonly three parts or heads are obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt ſets forth the <hi>principall Inſtrument</hi> of this ſtrange Gaole delivery; 'Tis <hi>Cyrus</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> whom the Lord doth <hi>call</hi> by name to this great ſervice; For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>[Spacus]</hi> that is in the Median language <hi>Canis,</hi> (ſo called becauſe he had been nurſed by a <hi>Bitch</hi>) he is ſirnamed <hi>[Coreſch]</hi> by the Perſians,
<note place="margin">Herodotus. Iuſtinus.</note> which amongſt them doth ſignifie <hi>a Lord.</hi> This ſtrange man is anointed, that is, authoriſed and fitted to this ſtrange work. The <hi>fitting</hi> of him lyes in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> in giving <hi>Strength</hi> unto him: (wiſdom and ſtrength are for the war) The Lord doth promiſe to <hi>hold his hand</hi> as the <hi>Scribe</hi> doth guide the hand of his unready ſcholar; or rather as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did put his hands upon the hands of <hi>Joaſh</hi> King of Iſrael, when he did ſhoot the arrow of the Lords deliverance, the arrow of deliverance from <hi>Syria,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.16, 17. So runneth the expreſſion of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord to Cyrus, whoſe right hand I have holden,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Next,</hi> the Lord doth as it were <hi>provide Pioners</hi> for him to further his march, by opening of gates, levelling of wayes, and removing all obſtacles and impediments; <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>I will looſe the loynes of Kings, to open before him the two-leaved gates, and the gates ſhall not be ſhut,</hi> verſ. 3. I <hi>will go before thee, and make the crooked places ſtreight,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But there is a <hi>third</hi> thing yet behind, and that is the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of war, a ſufficient <hi>treaſury</hi> for the work. This al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhall be ſupplyed, verſ. 3. <hi>And I will give thee the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of darkneſſe and hidden riches of ſecret places,</hi> &amp;c. Thus the Lord will be in ſtead of <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> of <hi>Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> and of <hi>Treaſurers,</hi> to fit <hi>Cyrus</hi> and his Armies for this great ſervice.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112329:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in caſe that all theſe three particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſhould not be enough to ſteele the hearts of the Jewes to ſet upon this hard work, and to hold out in it; the Lord in the next place, doth <hi>proclaime</hi> all his great <hi>Attributes</hi> before them to encourage them in their way. Thus when he was to put <hi>Moſes</hi> upon that great deſigne of bringing the people of Iſrael out of Egypt, Hee <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth</hi> His Name before him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14. <hi>I am that I am, thus ſhalt thou ſay unto the children of Iſrael, [I am] hath ſent me unto you.</hi> The like in <hi>Exod.</hi> 6. verſ. 3. where he telleth him of his great <hi>Name Jehovah,</hi> by which ſaith he, I was not known unto <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> This head of the Chapter runneth onward from the end of verſ. 4. to verſ. 14. It is one continued, loud, large <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation</hi> of the Lords <hi>excellencies</hi> and prerogatives royall, thereby to ſupport their ſpirits againſt all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties. The ſumme of the whole incouragement may be thus rendred; <hi>I can</hi> (ſaith God) and I will muſter and command all things <hi>from the riſing of the Sunne, and from the Weſt,</hi> verſ. 5. &amp; 6. both <hi>light and darkneſſe,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>the heavens, the skies, the earth,</hi> verſ. 8. All theſe will I mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and draw forth for this work, rather than it ſhall die in the birth: And as for <hi>that Potſheard, that Clay,</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, it ſhall herein know my love unto Iſrael, verſ. 9. and ſhall feele what it is for a <hi>creature</hi> to <hi>ſtrive</hi> with its <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> or for a <hi>birth</hi> to tax thoſe <hi>parents</hi> that begat and bare it, verſ. 10. This part reacheth to verſ. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The remainder, which is the <hi>third piece of the Chapter,</hi> is a kind of <hi>twiſted promiſe,</hi> partly reſpecting the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from <hi>Babylon</hi> in the <hi>letter;</hi> and partly (according to the uſual manner of the Prophets) <hi>interweaning</hi> ſome paſſages concerning <hi>Chriſt</hi> and ſpirituall redemption, in the <hi>myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112329:6"/>
            <p>The words of my Text,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Diviſion.,</note> if you looke upon them <hi>with reference</hi> to the bordering verſes, they are an <hi>abrupt Apoſtrophe.</hi> If you view them <hi>in themſelves</hi> without that reference, they are <hi>an Epanorthoſis</hi> or correction.</p>
            <p>Firſt looke upon them <hi>with reference</hi> to the bordering verſes;
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Relatively."</note> ſo you ſhal finde that this verſe of my text ſeems <hi>not</hi> at all to be <hi>of kin</hi> to other parts of the chapter. The whole <hi>ſeries</hi> ſtandeth thus; <hi>The Church</hi> having heard &amp; conſidered all the <hi>promiſes, prophecies</hi> and <hi>paſſages</hi> of this ſtrange work of ſalvation and redemption from Babylon, how that it ſhall be done <hi>by Cyrus,</hi> an heathen King, an enemie to the Iewes: and obſerving alſo that there were ſo many <hi>crooked places</hi> that muſt be made <hi>ſtreight,</hi> ſo many <hi>gates of braſſe</hi> that muſt be ſhattered and <hi>broken in pieces</hi> ver. 2. and having further conſidered ver. 8. that <hi>this</hi> ſame <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> muſt <hi>drop down from heaven</hi> above, as it were by a <hi>miracle;</hi> that it muſt come up <hi>from the earth</hi> beneath, as if it were from low and <hi>contemptible meanes:</hi> Nay fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally they having alſo ſeriouſly pondered that this grand redemption ſhall be done <hi>without price</hi> and without <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> as ver. 13. (and who will doe a worke without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? who goeth a warfare at his owne coſts? yet ſaith God) <hi>he ſhall build my City and he ſhall let go my captives, not for price, nor reward, ſaith the Lord of hoſts</hi> Having conſidered all theſe ſtrange curcumſtances &amp; rubs in the way, all theſe <hi>Meanders,</hi> theſe <hi>up-hills</hi> &amp; <hi>down-hills</hi> in the <hi>paſſage,</hi> and having lain them together, ſhe cryes out like <hi>one aſtoniſhed,</hi> and in a kind of <hi>abrupt Apoſtrophe</hi> doth <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt</hi> the Prophet in his Sermon with this mixed admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration twixt <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>faith [verily thou art a God that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thy ſelfe, O God of Iſrael the Saviour]</hi> that is, <hi>whilſt</hi> thou hideſt thy ſelfe, O God, yet thou art the <hi>Saviour</hi> of Iſrael.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112329:6"/>Thus with <hi>reference to the bordering verſes,</hi> the Text is an <hi>abrupt</hi> interrupting <hi>Apoſtrophe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, conſider the <hi>words in themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Abſolutely.</note> and they are a kind of EPANORTHOSIS, a <hi>correction:</hi> For in the <hi>former part</hi> of the verſe, the Church ſeemeth to <hi>trip,</hi> ſtumble, and ſtagger, at the ſtrangenes of the <hi>manner</hi> of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied deliverance from Babylon; it is carried on in ſuch an <hi>abſtruſe,</hi> intricate, unuſuall way and method, that ſhe cryes out as one at a loſſe, <hi>[verily thou art a God that hideſt thy ſelfe]</hi> Here is her trip, her ſtagger, her ſtumble at the ſtrange manner in the former part: But then ſhe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers</hi> her ſelfe againe in the <hi>latterpart</hi> to a <hi>confident per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſion</hi> of an undoubted <hi>good iſſue</hi> or end at laſt, concluding certainly that the upſhot will be <hi>wonderful ſalvation</hi> unto the <hi>Iſrael of God;</hi> though the maner be ſtrange &amp; various, yet the <hi>iſſue</hi> will be, ſhall be good and <hi>certaine:</hi> Though thou be (ſaith ſhe) a God that <hi>hideſt thy ſelfe,</hi> yet O God, I beleeve thou wilt be the <hi>Saviour of Iſrael.</hi> Thus ſhe trips in the firſt, and <hi>recovers</hi> her ſelfe in the <hi>latter,</hi> and you know the proverb, <hi>he that ſtumbles &amp; doth not fall, makes the more ſpeed in his way.</hi> This is the <hi>ſtate of the Text:</hi> So that the former part of it is a kind of <hi>muſing admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at the <hi>ſtrange manner</hi> of Gods proceeding; the latter part is a <hi>confident perſwaſion</hi> of the finall <hi>good iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I would be curious to <hi>mince a text,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Sub-divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> both thoſe <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall parts</hi> might admit of a more <hi>particular anatomie.</hi> As firſt in that ſtrange <hi>hidden manner</hi> of this work, there are <hi>three</hi> ſeverall ſteps or <hi>degrees:</hi> and <hi>as many</hi> more (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to them) are to be found in the certaine <hi>beleeved iſſue</hi> of this ſalvation.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>manner</hi> is implyed,
<list>
                  <item n="1">I. <hi>An obſcurity;</hi> 'tis an <hi>[hidden God]</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2. The <hi>willingnes</hi> of that obſcurity, a <hi>[ſelfe-hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding] God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112329:7"/>
                  <item n="3">3. The <hi>certainty of both,</hi> [verily] <hi>thou art ſuch a God.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>iſſue,</hi> there is an exact <hi>oppoſition</hi> to all thoſe three, both in quantity and quality. For
<list>
                  <item n="1">1. This <hi>hidden God</hi> was [notwithſtanding] the <hi>God [of Iſrael.]</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2. This <hi>ſelfe-hiding God</hi> was (even that while) a <hi>[Saviour.]</hi> And</item>
                  <item n="3">3. The <hi>certainty,</hi> expreſt in the aſſeveration <hi>[ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily]</hi> is anſwered and over-powered by an <hi>admiration,</hi> in the <hi>interjection</hi> [ô] as though the <hi>mouth</hi> of the ſpeaker had been too <hi>narrow</hi> for his <hi>heart</hi> and obſervation.</item>
               </list> And thus the whole <hi>tenour</hi> of the text doth runne ſomewhat like the <hi>beginning</hi> of Pſal. 73. ver. 1. <hi>Truly</hi> (or <hi>yet) God is good to Iſrael, even to ſuch as are of a clean heart.</hi> Why <hi>[truly]</hi> or <hi>[yet]?</hi> See the next verſe, ver. 2. <hi>but as for me my feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well-nigh ſlipt:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? ver. 3. <hi>For I was envious at the fooliſh when I ſaw the proſperity of the wicked.</hi> Marke, he <hi>recovered</hi> himſelfe in the <hi>iſſue,</hi> though he <hi>ſtumbled</hi> at the <hi>entrance.</hi> It ſeems that the Lords diſpenſations in thoſe dayes went on like this deliverance from Babylon; and this deliverance went on juſt (me thinkes) like the <hi>motions of a Clocke: Fixe</hi> your eyes ſtedfaſtly upon a Clocke while it is <hi>going,</hi> you ſhall only heare and ſee <hi>the ballance</hi> moving and clacking above, but you cannot perceive the <hi>poiſes</hi> making any motion that while, neither can you diſcerne the <hi>finger</hi> of the watch to goe forwards; but <hi>take off</hi> your eye for a while, leaving a <hi>marke</hi> upon the place, and then you ſhall finde eaſily <hi>[in facto eſſe]</hi> that the Clocke hath gone, though <hi>[in fieri]</hi> you could not perceive it in motion. <hi>Such</hi> was <hi>the carriage</hi> of this worke: While the people of God did ſtedfaſtly and continually <hi>fix</hi> their eyes upon it, it was advanced in ſuch an <hi>abſtruſe,</hi> intricate, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible way, that they could ſee <hi>no motion</hi> at all. Thus we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112329:7"/>reade in Ezra 4. ver. 24. <hi>Then ceaſed the worke of the houſe of God which is at Jeruſalem;</hi> and yet even <hi>then</hi> it <hi>ſcarcely ceaſed,</hi> for in the next Chapter, chapt. 5. the <hi>Prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyed,</hi> ver. 1. and the eminent men <hi>begun to build</hi> againe, ver. 2. &amp; 5. The <hi>ballance</hi> of the <hi>Clocke</hi> did continue their clacke, and at laſt the <hi>Clocke</hi> did ſtrike out.</p>
            <p>So much ought neceſſarily to be ſaid for <hi>draining,</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, and trenching the <hi>ground</hi> for a <hi>foundation.</hi> Now (not to detaine you any longer from the thing that I doe principally intend) the <hi>Obſervation</hi> from the whole Text and Context thus briefly explained, divided, deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, muſt run thus: That,
<q>
                  <hi>Gods great ſalvations of his people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                  <hi>but eſpecially from Babylon, are commonly carried on in a myſtery.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Here is <hi>ſalvation,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Saviour:</hi> And ſo <hi>great</hi> a ſalvation, that it ſtrikes the beholding Church or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet into an <hi>admiration,</hi> they cannot expreſſe it without an interjection, <hi>O God of Iſrael the Saviour.</hi> And that this ſalvation is <hi>from Babylon,</hi> the whole tenour, graine and ſtraine of the Hiſtory doth declare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salvation</hi> is nothing elſe but the <hi>putting</hi> of a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>ſafe condition;</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Salvation, what.</note> and it is ſometimes taken <hi>actively</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>Author;</hi> As <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Stand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of God;</hi> And ſo I ſay here, the <hi>Lords ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> Sometimes ſalvation is taken <hi>paſsively,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>receiver;</hi> As you may reade in the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.7. <hi>O that the ſalvation of Iſrael were come out of Zion;</hi> And ſo I ſay, the Lords <hi>ſalvation of his people:</hi> Therefore <hi>both</hi> thoſe ſignifications are in the Poſition; and both thoſe ſorts may be further conſidered, firſt, with <hi>reſpect</hi> to their <hi>ſubject,</hi> whether as <hi>common,</hi> publique, or generall, reſpecting a <hi>whole Nation, Church</hi> or <hi>people;</hi> or as <hi>particular,</hi> private or ſpeciall, of <hi>a place, member,</hi> or <hi>perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:112329:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Next,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>object,</hi> or <hi>[materia circa quam.]</hi> So there is a <hi>ſalvation [in ſpiritualibus &amp; Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticis]</hi> a ſpiritual, a religious ſalvation, that is the ſame with <hi>[Reformation.]</hi> And there is a ſalvation <hi>[in Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, Civilibus &amp; ſecularibus]</hi> a ſalvation in politique things, and this is the ſame with <hi>[Deliverance.]</hi> In this place you muſt take in <hi>both, Reformation</hi> and <hi>Deliverance,</hi> becauſe both are expreſſed in this <hi>Prophecie,</hi> as we may gather out of <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.28. <hi>Saying to Ieruſalem, Thou ſhalt be built;</hi> there is the Civill or politique ſalvation, <hi>the State-ſalvation,</hi> the <hi>Deliverance: And to the Temple, Tthy foundation ſhall be layd;</hi> there is the Spirituall and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall ſalvation, the <hi>Church-ſalvation,</hi> which is the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>accordingly</hi> I ſhall carry on my doctrine, both in the <hi>Demonſtrative</hi> and <hi>applicative</hi> parts of it, uſing the word <hi>[ſalvation]</hi> in both theſe acceptions, for <hi>Reformati</hi>-and <hi>Deliverance:</hi> And thus <hi>Gods great ſalvations of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, eſpecially from Babylon, are carryed-on in a myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Babylon</hi> in ſcripture is of <hi>two ſorts.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Babylon, which, Easterne.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, there is <hi>literal, Eaſterne, Aſiatique Babylon.</hi> This was the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Chaldea,</hi> &amp; ſometimes of the world. Of this we reade commonly in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and it is meant <hi>immediately</hi> in the Text.</p>
            <p>Next,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Westerne.</note> there is <hi>Myſticall, Westerne, Europaean Babylon;</hi> this is <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> and it was ſometimes the Queen of the Nations: Of it we doe reade commonly in the <hi>New Testament.</hi> This is <hi>alſo</hi> included in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>In a Myſtery] A myſtery <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and for the ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſounding <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth ſignifie an <hi>hidden,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Myſtery, why.</note> 
               <hi>abstruſe, ſecret</hi> matter, a thing <hi>ſhut up</hi> under bars and locks from <hi>common ſenſe</hi> and <hi>carnall reaſon.</hi> It doth include theſe two conditions.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112329:8"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>[Reſpectu Dei]</hi> in reſpect <hi>of God,</hi> it is an act or work not of his common, generall, ordinary providence; but of his particular, ſpeciall, extraordinary power, wiſdome, juſtice, mercy; 'tis not only the work of his <hi>hands,</hi> but of his <hi>finger;</hi> as the Aegyptian-Magitians ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged concerning the plague of <hi>Lice</hi> (Exod. 8. verſe 18, 19.) when they ſaw that their inchantments did faile them in that particular, they ſaid unto Pharaoh, <hi>This is the [Finger] of the Lord.</hi> Thus in reſpect of the Lord, a myſterious carriage of a buſineſſe 'tis (as Iſaiah ſays els where, Chap. 28. verſ. 21.) <hi>His worke, his ſtrange worke, his act, his ſtrange act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, <hi>[Reſpectu nostri]</hi> in reſpect of <hi>us</hi> men, it is <hi>hard to be underſtood,</hi> 'tis to the common multitude as a thing <hi>locked up</hi> in a ſtrange language, as 1 Cor. 14.2. (I may allude at leaſt) <hi>For he that ſpeaketh in an unknowne tongue, ſpeaketh not unto men, but unto God, for no man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth</hi> (or heareth him) <hi>howbeit in the ſpirit he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth [Myſteries.]</hi> In ſhort, a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> is to the generality of men, a <hi>paradox,</hi> a <hi>riddle,</hi> a ſecret that doth require a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation;</hi> as Dan. 2.28. <hi>There is a God in Heaven that revealeth ſecrets</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the Septuagint.</p>
            <p>Thus much I meane by a myſterious carriage in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, <hi>viz.</hi> when a ſalvation is wrought out in a courſe, <hi>beſides, beyond,</hi> or <hi>againſt,</hi> the beaten rode of <hi>common</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence &amp; <hi>carnall</hi> capacities. Let us borrow but one verſ. more to expreſſe it alluſively: See, Pro. 30. verſe 18. <hi>There be three things which are too wonderfull for me, yea foure which I know not:</hi> reade verſe 19. <hi>the way of an Eagle in the ayre, the way of a Serpent upon a rock, and the way of a Ship in the middeſt of the Sea.</hi> Juſt ſuch is uſually the way of the Lord in carrying on his great ſalvations, and eſpecially from Babylon. Let us ſeverally conſider thoſe three compariſons.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112329:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The way of an Eagle in the Aire,]</hi> Amongſt all the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements,</hi> the <hi>aire</hi> alone is <hi>inviſible</hi> and leaſt palpable; it doth moſt <hi>eaſily give</hi> a paſſage to any naturall body, and as ſuddenly comes together again. Amongſt all <hi>fowles</hi> of the heaven, the <hi>Eagle</hi> is accounted ſtrongeſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth fly very <hi>ſwiftly;</hi> and being a bird of prey, her motion is exceeding <hi>various</hi> too, according to the courſe of the game that is before her: Who then can gueſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or trace-out afterwards, the way of an Eagle in the aire?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The way of a Serpent upon a Rock]</hi> is no leſſe hidden. Oh! how doth this creeping creature wind, wave, and weave it as ſhe goes? what felf-obliterating chiverdils and indentures are made in her motion? Now the <hi>head</hi> doth point this way, in a moment it ſtands to the other hand; 'tis hard for him that meeteth her, to gueſſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no ſhe be comming towards him: But eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when a Serpent goeth <hi>[upon a Rocke]</hi> then there is no meanes to <hi>heare</hi> her motion as in the ſand &amp; amongſt the leaves, or to <hi>ſee</hi> and trace it as in the duſt and clay; no <hi>noyſe,</hi> no <hi>impreſsion</hi> is made to help the <hi>eare</hi> or <hi>eye</hi> of him that ſeeketh her way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the way of the Ship in the middeſt of the Sea]</hi> is more abſtruſe and uncertaine then both the former. There are <hi>three principles</hi> of variation and uncertainty in her moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Firſt, the <hi>wind</hi> above, that <hi>bloweth where it liſteth, and we heare the ſound thereof, but know not whence it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, nor whither it goeth.</hi> Next, the <hi>waters</hi> beneath are the moſt inconſtant of Elements; for (beſides that they are driven of fierce winds) their own naturall ebbings and flowings, are a dayly <hi>conſtant inconſtancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But (laſtly) the greateſt principle of uncertainty, is the <hi>minde</hi> and pleaſure of her <hi>Pilot</hi> within, who at his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112329:9"/>will doth often turne her to <hi>halfe a point</hi> againſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions both of winds and waters. In ſhort, ſhe finds <hi>no path</hi> before her, ſhe leaves <hi>no tract</hi> behind her, and all her movers, above, beneath, with in, are moſt uncertaine. Who then can know the way of a Ship in the middeſt of the <hi>Sea?</hi> So, <hi>not-to-be-gueſſed, not-to-be-traced</hi> are the Lords carriages of theſe kinds of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>My Doctrine is ſomewhat like that peice of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> wheele, which he calleth <hi>[Rotam in rota]</hi> Ezek. 1.16. <hi>Their appearance and their worke were as it were a wheele in the middeſt of a wheele:</hi> So here is a <hi>Doctrine</hi> in the middeſt of a <hi>Doctrine.</hi> The firſt is as it were the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Theſis</hi> concerning Gods great ſalvations indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely. The ſecond is as an <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> drawne out of the wombe of that Theſis, concerning the redemption from Babylon in <hi>particular.</hi> And <hi>accordingly</hi> I ſhall have an eye <hi>diſtinctly</hi> both in my <hi>demonſtrative</hi> and <hi>applicative</hi> parts, looking upon theſe two, ſeverally and apart.</p>
            <p>Firſt then <hi>Demonſtratively,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In Theſi.</note> concerning the <hi>generall</hi> the <hi>Theſis,</hi> that Gods great ſalvations of his people, are commonly carryed on in a myſtery. O what rare <hi>Maps</hi> of ſaving <hi>wonders,</hi> what admirable <hi>anatomies</hi> of publique <hi>mercies</hi> could I here ſpread before your eyes this day! Only let us cropoff ſome <hi>full eares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt obſerve that great <hi>preſervation</hi> of <hi>old Jacob</hi> and his family by their removall from <hi>Canaan</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Iacobs Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</note> in the time of the Famine: How ſtrangely was that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance brought about! The <hi>deſigne</hi> was to preſerve <hi>Jacob</hi> and his poſterity, and to make a way for that great worke of <hi>redemption</hi> out of Egypt which followed after: But marke the <hi>method;</hi> Firſt <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who by his owne dreames and his Fathers hopes was to be the <hi>glory</hi> and prop of the family, he muſt be given <hi>for loſt</hi> to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112329:10"/>his brethren, himſelf: His <hi>Father</hi> gives him for <hi>torne in pieces,</hi> his <hi>Brethren</hi> doe ſell him into Egypt for a <hi>bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave,</hi> and there he is caſt into priſon by <hi>Potiphar</hi> after he had been firſt advanced. So that now not only the <hi>Fathers</hi> hopes are dead and buried, but <hi>Joſephs owne faith</hi> is put to the <hi>tryall;</hi> and all this to <hi>make way</hi> for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er deliverance. Doe not theſe things now looke like a ſalvation? Nay farther yet, old <hi>Jacob</hi> muſt be <hi>neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by Famine</hi> to ſend downe into Egypt to buy food, and there he muſt firſt <hi>loſe</hi> his Son <hi>Simeon;</hi> and next his deareſt <hi>Benjamin</hi> muſt be ſent and loſt in his owne and brethrens apprehenſions: And yet all this appeareth at laſt to be nothing elſe but a meere <hi>plot</hi> of <hi>mercy,</hi> a very <hi>ambuſhment</hi> of <hi>Providence</hi> for the greater <hi>advantage</hi> and <hi>advancement</hi> of the <hi>whole family,</hi> as you ſee in the <hi>iſſue.</hi> For firſt all the <hi>brethren of Joſeph</hi> with their houſhol had thereby their <hi>preſervation</hi> and <hi>preferment</hi> whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they had periſhed by famine. Secondly, <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin</hi> who was the moſt hazarded and loſt man amongſt them when the cup was found in his ſacke; he hath gotten a <hi>multiplied portion.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Iacob</hi> himſelfe (the father) he doth gaine <hi>five ſonnes</hi> for <hi>one,</hi> that is, for his deare <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> whom he conceived to be loſt, he receiveth the ſame <hi>Ioſeph</hi> againe with an addition of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes;</hi> and alſo two of his owne ſons whom he conceived to be loſt, <hi>[Simeon</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,]</hi> are caſt in to boot: Thus five are returned for one. This was an ambuſhment of mercy. And finally as for <hi>Ioſeph</hi> him ſelfe, he muſt have <hi>a double</hi> bleſſing and portion, and is made the <hi>head</hi> of two Tribes; one of which (Ephraim) in ſhort time after the throne was erected, did get away <hi>ten</hi> of the twelve Tribes from the Scepter of Iudah. Was not this a myſtery of myſteries? Thus farre concerning the ſalvation of <hi>Iacob</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112329:10"/>and his family when they were <hi>carried from</hi> Canaan into Egypt.</p>
            <p>But in the next place,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</note> the <hi>preſervation</hi> of the ſeed of <hi>Iacob in Egypt,</hi> and their <hi>returne</hi> from thence to Canaan againe, at the end of foure hundred and thirty yeares, was <hi>more admirable</hi> then their firſt going thither, their ſtrange <hi>preſervation</hi> in Egypt was ſhadowed in that Emblem of <hi>a fiery buſh</hi> not conſumed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. ver. 2. <hi>And the Angell of the Lord appeared unto [Moſes] in a flame of fire out of the midst of a buſh,</hi> &amp;c. a token of Iſraels continuance in the midſt of the <hi>iron-fiery-furnace.</hi> Their ſalvation or deliverance was in this manner. <hi>Moſes</hi> (not while he was in favour in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, but) after that he was a <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive,</hi> an <hi>exile</hi> being a <hi>ſtammering ſhepherd</hi> muſt be the principall <hi>instrument</hi> in the work; and hee together with his brother <hi>Aaron,</hi> (another contemptible Levite) with <hi>a rod</hi> in their hands, muſt fetch out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt in <hi>ſpite</hi> of an hardned King, and all his <hi>Magicians,</hi> (how many gueſſe yee?) <hi>ſix hundred thouſand men,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a mixt multitude with women and children. Hee that can deny this to be a heape, a <hi>cluster</hi> of wonders, let himſelfe be <hi>recorded</hi> for a wonder of ſtupidity.</p>
            <p>Once more; a <hi>third inſtance,</hi> in the time of the <hi>Iudges;</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">From Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian.</note> See but that great ſalvation and deliverance of Iſrael out of the hand of the <hi>Midianites</hi> and their confederates; and let us caſt our eye equally upon both parties, the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors</hi> and the <hi>Delivered.</hi> Firſt, look upon the <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors;</hi> conſider their power, their cruelty. In <hi>Iudg.</hi> 6. in the firſt verſe you ſhall reade that <hi>Iſrael</hi> had ſerved an apprentiſhip of <hi>ſeven yeares</hi> under their tyranny. In the 2, 3, 4, and 5. verſes, you ſhall reade, that poore Iſrael was faine to run into <hi>dens</hi> of the <hi>mountaines,</hi> and <hi>caves,</hi> and <hi>ſtrong-holds,</hi> that their <hi>fruits</hi> were deſtroyed aſſoone
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112329:11"/>as they came forth; that their enemies came up as <hi>graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers,</hi> and left <hi>no ſustenance</hi> for Iſrael, neither <hi>ſheepe,</hi> nor <hi>oxe,</hi> nor <hi>aſſe;</hi> and this fury ſtill increaſed, for verſ. 5. they came up with their <hi>cattell and their tents, and they came as graſhoppers for multitude, for both they and their camels were without number.</hi> That for the enemies part. Next, look upon Iſrael the <hi>Delivered,</hi> and conſider their power and ſtrength. Their <hi>Generall,</hi> would you know what he was? He was <hi>Gideon,</hi> a <hi>Threſher,</hi> afterward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Jerubbaal,</hi> a man called away from the <hi>barne,</hi> from the threſhing floore, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 6.16. <hi>His family poor in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> and <hi>himſelf</hi> the <hi>least</hi> in that poor family; a man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the very <hi>flaile</hi> to be a <hi>Captain-Generall.</hi> And for his <hi>Forces,</hi> it is true, at the firſt they were a conſiderable number; they were (the text ſaith) <hi>two and thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand;</hi> but then the Lord falleth to <hi>leſſening</hi> of them. Firſt, he beginneth with <hi>a Proclamation,</hi> and thereupon ſome <hi>two and twenty thouſand</hi> of them do go away. Next, the Lord hath another experiment, <hi>of lapping,</hi> and by that meanes hee ſends away all the remaining ten thouſand, except only poore <hi>three hundred;</hi> So that now about the <hi>hundredth part</hi> of <hi>Gideons</hi> forces is left. This <hi>handfull</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of <hi>Gideon</hi> the <hi>Threſher,</hi> muſt go againſt the <hi>numberleſſe Midianites.</hi> But yet an <hi>handfull</hi> with choyce <hi>weapons,</hi> at ſome advantages, may do great things? True, but in the next place looke upon their <hi>Armes,</hi> both defenſive and offenſive, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.20. they were to go with <hi>empty pitchers,</hi> and <hi>lamps within the pitchers</hi> in one hand, and in the other hand they muſt hold a <hi>trumpet,</hi> and with <hi>blowing</hi> thoſe <hi>trumpets, breaking</hi> the <hi>pitchers,</hi> and <hi>holding out</hi> the <hi>lamps,</hi> they ſhall beat the <hi>Midianites.</hi> Here is a <hi>Mystery</hi> with a witneſſe; A numberleſſe armie, totally routed and cut in pieces without any weapon appearing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112329:11"/>againſt them, <hi>broken</hi> in pieces with the breaking of pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, <hi>frightned</hi> with the ſight of lamps, and utterly <hi>blown away</hi> by the ſound of trumpets. This is Gods great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion carried on in a Myſtery.</p>
            <p>Yea, but what is all this to ſalvation from <hi>Babylon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I confeſſe is the HYPOTHESIS,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">In Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſi.</note> and may as ſtrangely and fully be ſhewen and <hi>proved</hi> as the <hi>generall;</hi> even that Gods ſalvations <hi>from Babylon</hi> are carried-on in a myſtery. There are <hi>two Babylons</hi> mentioned in Scripture. Firſt, <hi>Babylon</hi> the <hi>Easterne,</hi> which was that in <hi>Chaldea,</hi> the <hi>literall Babylon;</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> the <hi>Westerne,</hi> which is that in <hi>Italy, Rome,</hi> the <hi>mysticall Babylon.</hi> Concerning <hi>both</hi> theſe, I could ſhew you diſtinctly that Gods great ſalvations out of them, are commonly carried-on in a myſtery.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">From Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</note> concerning ſalvation and redemption out of the hand of <hi>literall,</hi> Eaſterne, <hi>Chaldean-Babylon,</hi> we find no leſſe then <hi>foure</hi> whole <hi>bookes</hi> of the Scriptures ſpent to ſhew the extraordinary deliverances of Gods people from thence. <hi>Two</hi> of theſe books are <hi>historicall,</hi> as <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> other two are <hi>propheticall, as Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zechariah.</hi> It would be too long for me to epitomize all the expreſſions of thoſe books, and of ſome others, which doe ſhew the wonderfull myſterious carriage of that worke: Only take notice of <hi>two places</hi> to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of that <hi>viſion</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> which, as I conceive, doth typifie the Jewiſh returne from Babylon, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1. The whole viſion is large, in it there is mention of a <hi>whirle-wind</hi> out of the North, a great <hi>cloud,</hi> a ſelfe-infol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>fire,</hi> and out of the midſt thereof the <hi>colour of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> verſ. 4. Alſo out of the ſame midſt, the likeneſſe of <hi>foure living creatures,</hi> like men, verſ. 5. they had <hi>foure faces, foure wings,</hi> they had the <hi>feet</hi> of <hi>Calves,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:112329:12"/>the <hi>hands</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 6, 7, &amp;c. Strange <hi>mixtures</hi> and <hi>varieties!</hi> I will only pitch upon that piece which concernes the <hi>wheeles.</hi> Thoſe <hi>wheeles</hi> (as Interpreters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) do ſignifie the Lords <hi>providence:</hi> and the <hi>motions</hi> of the wheeles, the ſeverall <hi>acts</hi> and turnings of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the deliverance of his people from Babylon the Eaſterne; therefore, verſ. 18. it is ſaid the <hi>wheeles were full of eyes round about;</hi> (The <hi>eyes of the Lord do runne thorow the world</hi>) But I would eſpecially take notice there of the <hi>[involucra providentiae]</hi> the intricate involutions and incirclings of thoſe wheeles; it is ſet downe, ver. 16. Their worke was, <hi>as it were a wheele in the middle of a wheele,</hi> to ſignifie, the <hi>eccentricall</hi> and <hi>concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical motions</hi> of that peoples return from Babylon, where <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was now a captive amongſt them, as you may reade verſ. 1.</p>
            <p>But a <hi>more full</hi> and cleare place to ſhew the myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the deliverance of Iſrael from <hi>Babylon the Eaſterne,</hi> is that in the <hi>Prophecie of Zechariah.</hi> Look but upon that one Text in Chap. 1. verſ. 8. <hi>I ſaw by night, and behold a Man riding upon a red horſe, and hee ſtood among the Myrtle trees that were in the bottome, and behind him were theſe red horſes, ſpeckled and white.</hi> This <hi>Man</hi> is CHRIST; Theſe <hi>horſes</hi> with him are his <hi>Angels;</hi> and their <hi>deſigne</hi> is to bring the Jewes out of <hi>Babylon the Easterne,</hi> where they had lyen under Gods indignation theſe <hi>threeſcore and ten</hi> yeares, as you may reade, verſ. 12. But marke how that redemption is carried in the clouds, there are no leſſe then <hi>five notes</hi> of obſcurity in that verſe, ſignifying the Myſterious progreſſe of the worke.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is ſaid that this viſion was in the <hi>[night]</hi> both in the night <hi>(that is)</hi> of <hi>adverſity,</hi> and in the night of <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112329:12"/>Little comfort, few Prophets were left to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive or direct them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This man is in <hi>[a bottome]</hi> that is, <hi>obſcurely</hi> placed out of ſight: And as if that were not enough;</p>
            <p n="3">3. In this bottome he ſtoode among the <hi>[Myrtle-trees:]</hi> There was a <hi>grove</hi> of tall trees, in the <hi>center</hi> of a vallie; ſo that the Jewes might well have ſaid unto him as here in the text, <hi>Verily</hi> thou art a God that hideſt thy ſelf. But that is not all.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His forces, his Auxiliaries, ſtoode <hi>[behind]</hi> him, ſaith the text, that is, they were not only covered by the valley and the myrtle trees, but they were covered by the interpoſition of Chriſts perſon too; they were trebly covered, with the <hi>valley,</hi> with the <hi>myrtle-trees,</hi> and with <hi>Chriſt</hi> that ſtoode before them. And</p>
            <p n="5">5. This <hi>[Speckling]</hi> or <hi>dapling</hi> of the horſes is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, it doth ſhew the interchangeable, <hi>party coloured</hi> texture of that worke; yea the red and the white with the ſpeckled, do ſhew the mixture of peace and bloud that they did troop together in this worke.</p>
            <p>But here ſome might object, True, true, all this is <hi>confeſſed,</hi> that great-ſalvations in generall, and in ſpeciall thoſe from Eaſterne Babylon have bin, are carried on in a myſtery; but <hi>now</hi> ſuch <hi>wonders</hi> and miracles doe <hi>ceaſe;</hi> what is all this unto us in theſe times?</p>
            <p>In the next place therefore,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">From We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</note> I will ſhew that ſalvation from <hi>Babylon</hi> the <hi>Weſterne,</hi> from <hi>Romiſh Babylon</hi> (that is, the ſalvation we are now upon] muſt alſo be carried on in a myſtery.</p>
            <p>For this purpoſe, firſt I would commend unto you a choyce <hi>text</hi> for <hi>our times,</hi> me thinks it is as a <hi>word upon the wheeles</hi> in theſe our dayes, 'tis <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. where you have a <hi>prophetique viſion,</hi> a viſion of an <hi>Image, whoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112329:13"/>head is of gold, the breaſt and armes of ſilver, the belly and thighs of braſſe, the legs of Iron, and the feet part iron, and part clay;</hi> Expoſitors doe conceive that this foure-fold image doth ſignifie the <hi>foure</hi> famous <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the world: The <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> (as it is commonly called) the <hi>Grecian</hi> and the <hi>Roman.</hi> Monarchies. The firſt three of theſe are paſt, and (without queſtion) we are come now to the lower part of the fourth, I meane the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> is removed, and we doe ſee the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Iron and Clay,</hi> whether you take the iron and clay for the <hi>diviſion</hi> of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> into the <hi>Weſterne</hi> and <hi>Eaſterne</hi> according to verſe 42. <hi>And as the toes of the feet were part of iron and part of clay, ſo the Kingdoms ſhall be partly ſtrong, and partly broaken,</hi> (or brittle;) the Eaſterne Empire was firſt broken off: Or whether you will underſtand a kind of <hi>compounding</hi> of ſucceſſion between the <hi>Romane</hi> and the <hi>Germane Empires:</hi> Or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (laſtly) a <hi>mingling</hi> and dawbing of the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>temporall</hi> (that is, the <hi>Imperiall</hi> and <hi>Papall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> powers</hi> together; yet ſtill, wee are come to the <hi>feete</hi> of the Image, and to the very <hi>toes</hi> of thoſe feete, which are this Babylon the Weſterne in its preſent condition; for both branches of the proper Romane Empire are withered, and the <hi>Germane Eagle</hi> was never ſo ſtrip'd of her plumes as now: Yea the very <hi>Papacie</hi> of late doth ſhed her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall feathers continually: So that both <hi>Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chronologie,</hi> and <hi>common ſenſe,</hi> do evince, that the Image doth ſtand at beſt but <hi>on tip-toe;</hi> and the time is at hand, (I conceive it is preſent) in which it ſhall be throwne downe and utterly aboliſhed. But (you will aske me) <hi>how</hi> muſt it be throwne downe? by what meanes ſhall Gods people be delivered out of the hands of this Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Babylon? Truely by as <hi>ſtrange meanes</hi> as ever was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112329:13"/>reade of; See the 34. and 44. verſes of the chapaer: Firſt (in the 34. verſe) <hi>Thou ſaweſt till that a ſtone was cut out without hands</hi> (here is a myſtery, a ſtone cut out without hands, or <hi>which was not in hand) which ſmote the Image upon his feete which were of iron and clay; and brake them to pieces.</hi> This ſtone is Jeſus Chriſt, (as Matt. 21.42.) <hi>The ſtone which the builders rejected, the ſame is become the head of the corner;</hi> (verſe 44.) <hi>and whoſoever ſhall fall on this ſtone, ſhall be broken, but on whomſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever it ſhall fall, it will grinde him to powder.</hi> This Scripture is moſt exactly true concerning <hi>Chriſts gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in his Church, he will cruſh all oppoſitions as the <hi>potters veſſels.</hi> Againe, this Stone is <hi>cut out</hi> of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>without hands,</hi> &amp;c. That is, the <hi>Image</hi> ſhall be <hi>caſt downe,</hi> and the <hi>kingdome of Chriſt</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſet up,</hi> not by common carnall might and meanes, but in a ſpeciall and <hi>divine manner,</hi> for ſo it followeth in <hi>Daniels</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (verſe 44.45.) <hi>In the dayes of theſe Kings</hi> (at the cloſe of the <hi>laſt Empire) ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a Kingdome which ſhall never be deſtroyed, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall not be left to other people, but it ſhall breake in pieces and conſume all theſe Kingdomes, and it ſhall ſtand for ever. For aſmuch as thou ſaneſt that the ſtone was cut out of the mountaine without hands, and that it brake in pieces the iron, the braſſe, the clay, the ſilver, and the gold: The great God hath made knowne to the King what ſhall come to paſſe hereafter, &amp;c.</hi> I could wiſh that this ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>place of Daniel</hi> might come often into the thoughts of all our ſerious active ſpirits in <hi>theſe times</hi> for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement: And the rather,
<note place="margin">Mariana. Cornel. à Lapide, &amp; alii.</note> becauſe I finde that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> themſelves doe fall-in with my preſent interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſo far, that they have much a-doe to make ſuch a retreat as may ſeeme to excuſe the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112329:14"/>the names of Antichriſt and Babylon. <hi>Another viſion</hi> of the foure Monarchies like unto this, is to be ſeene, <hi>Daniel</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Adde to theſe, that place of the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> (which is, as it were, the Book of <hi>Daniel</hi> in the <hi>New Testament) Revel.</hi> 14. verſ. 6, 7, 8. there 'tis ſhewne that the ſalvation of Gods people from Babylon the myſticall, ſhall bee carried on in a myſtery, verſ. 6. <hi>And I ſaw another An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell fly in the midst of heaven, having the everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell to</hi> PREACH <hi>unto them that dwell on the earth,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>ſaying with a loud voice, Feare God, and give glory to him, for the houre of his judgement is come, &amp;c.</hi> Hereupon in the eighth verſe, there <hi>followed another Angell, ſaying, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon is fallen, is fallen, that great City, &amp;c. Fallen?</hi> why, what ayled her? <hi>What</hi> was it that threw her downe? Surely it was nothing but the <hi>Angell</hi> that did fly in the midſt of heaven, having an <hi>everlaſting Goſpell</hi> to preach unto them that dwell upon the earth: It was meerly the <hi>preaching of the Goſpell,</hi> if you will know it. So that it ſeemes the Lord will throw downe Babylon the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, juſt as he threw downe the <hi>walls of Jericho,</hi> with an <hi>holy blaſt,</hi> by the breath of the Goſpell; it ſhall be <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched flat to the ground.</hi> No marvell that our <hi>Prelates</hi> were ſo angry with <hi>Lecturers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another expreſsion</hi> of her overthrow might be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.13, 14, 15, 16. I will but name it, becauſe my reverend Brother in the morning hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented me. And Chap. 18. verſ. 2. where you ſhall find that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall be <hi>thrown down</hi> meerly by Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <hi>ſupernaturall working</hi> upon the <hi>ſpirits</hi> of thoſe men that were formerly <hi>friends</hi> and <hi>factors</hi> for the Whore: For firſt 'tis ſaid, verſe 13. that, <hi>theſe</hi> (that is, the <hi>ten hornes,</hi> which are <hi>tea Kings) have one mind, and ſhal give
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112329:14"/>their power and ſtrength unto the Beaſt.</hi> Verſe 14. <hi>Theſe ſhall make war with the Lambe.</hi> Here they doe unite and <hi>agree</hi> well enough <hi>to perſecute</hi> the Saints: but reade on to verſe 16. there they <hi>fall upon</hi> the Whore their late mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and miſtreſſe; <hi>The ten hornes which thou ſaweſt, theſe ſhall hate the Whore, and make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh and burne her with fire:</hi> A ſtrange <hi>alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> indeed! But how could ſuch <hi>neare friends</hi> fallin-to ſuch <hi>bitter enmity</hi> ſo ſuddenly? No cauſe at all but this, verſ. 17. <hi>for God hath put into their hearts,</hi> both to unite and fall off againe.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee not onely Gods great ſalvations of his people in generall, but eſpecially thoſe from Babylon, are to be carried-on in a myſtery.</p>
            <p>But <hi>is it not ſtrange</hi> that the Lord doth delight thus
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt.</note> to obſcure and hide himſelfe in the carriage of his great works? Would it not do better (according to our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and apprehenſions) if they were carried-on in the <hi>common rode</hi> of ordinary providence, ſo that every man might ſee them <hi>before</hi> him whileſt they are a doing, as well as <hi>behind</hi> him, when they are done?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, the nature of man is apt thus to reaſon,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> as <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 13. verſ. 3. and <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> chap. 12. verſ. 1. did. And I could anſwer ſuch queſtions with Saint <hi>Paul's, O homo tu qui &amp;c.</hi>—Rom. 9.20. <hi>Nay, but oh man who art thou that replyest against God?</hi> But that I may <hi>ſatisfie,</hi> as well as <hi>confute,</hi> I ſhal adde, that there are reaſons to ſhew that it is not only fit, but neceſſary, yea, <hi>triply neceſſary,</hi> that ſuch great ſalvations (eſpecially from Babylon) ſhould be myſteriouſly carried-on. 'Tis <hi>neceſſary,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. For the <hi>Lords greater glory.</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">The grounds</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. For his <hi>Peoples greater good.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. For his <hi>Enemies greater confuſion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:112329:15"/>
            <p>Firſt, the Lord doth thus hide himſelf whilſt he is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
<note n="1" place="margin" type="runSum">For Gods greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> for his <hi>owne greater glory.</hi> There is a cleare and full place to this particular, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.2. <hi>It is the glory of God to conceale a thing, but the honour of Kings is to ſearch out a matter,</hi> REM ABSCONDERE, that is, ſo to hide both <hi>himſelfe</hi> and his <hi>worke,</hi> that men may not be able be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand to <hi>gueſſe</hi> at him whither he will go next; nor yet to <hi>trace</hi> after him, when he is gone before. The latter expreſſion, namely, [That no man might go <hi>after him</hi>] is to be found in <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.13, 14. <hi>Conſider the work of God, for who can make that ſtreight, which he hath made crooked?</hi> And verſ. 14. <hi>In the day of proſperity be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyfull, but in the day of adverſity conſider; God alſo hath ſet the one over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other, to the end that man ſhould find nothing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him.</hi> Marke this, <hi>[God hath ſet the one over againſt the other, to the end that man ſhould find nothing after him]</hi> that is, the Lord doth incurvate his workes, he doth intricate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and (to our apprehenſion) promiſcuouſly <hi>mingle the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and effects of his common providence, he doth <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe</hi> his ground, he doth go on, as it were, <hi>by jumps,</hi> that ſo the wit of man may not be able to trace and follow him, but may ſit downe admiring the <hi>depths</hi> of his <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of his <hi>power:</hi> He doth leave ſo much print of his foot-ſteps as to <hi>convince the Atheiſt,</hi> that he went that way, and yet ſo little as to <hi>puzzle the Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt</hi> to find out the manner of his going.</p>
            <p>And 'tis abundantly for the Lords glory in <hi>all</hi> his <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes</hi> thus to <hi>conceale a matter.</hi> Every common <hi>Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is able to paint a plaine piece of worke,
<note place="margin">Eraſm. Adag.</note> 
               <hi>[Simulare cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſum]</hi> as the proverbe is; to paint a tree or a bough, but hee is an <hi>Artist</hi> indeed that is able to draw forth a <hi>ſhadowed piece.</hi> Every indifferent good ſouldier is able to fight pell-mell, or upon a party, hand to hand; but he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112329:15"/>is the skilful man that is able to <hi>order an ambuſhment,</hi> that can <hi>manage a ſtratagem.</hi> Beleeve it brethren, therefore doth the Lord draw his ſalvations in <hi>ſhadowed works,</hi> that you may ſee the depth of his wiſdome; therefore doth the Lord uſe to overcome by <hi>ambuſhments,</hi> that ſo the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>grace</hi> unto his people, and the glory of his <hi>wiſdome</hi> even amongſt his enemies, may be the greater. That is the firſt ground, <hi>for his owne greater glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond ground</hi> why he carries his worke in a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, is for the <hi>greater good of his people.</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin" type="runSum">For the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly's greater good.</note> You have ſo choyce a place to this purpoſe in the booke of <hi>Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy,</hi> that it alone may ſuffice, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. beginning at ver. 2. <hi>And thou ſhalt remember all the way which the Lord thy God led thee theſe forty yeers in the wilderneſſe, to humble thee, and to prove thee, to know what was in thine heart, whether thou wouldeſt keepe his Comandements or no; And he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled thee, and ſuffered thee to hunger, and fed thee with Manna, which thou kneweſt not, neither did thy fathers know, that he might make thee know, that man doth not live by bread only, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord doth man live: Thy rayment waxed not old upon thee, neither did thy feete ſwell theſe forty yeers.</hi> God could have carried on <hi>Iſrael</hi> in a <hi>ſhorter time</hi> and in a <hi>direct way,</hi> not in ſuch a maze and labyrinth through the wilderneſſe forty yeers together; he could have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them through within <hi>forty moneths:</hi> Hee could have <hi>fed</hi> them <hi>from the earth</hi> if it had pleaſed him, and could have preſerved them ſo as they ſhould never have bin <hi>ſtraitned</hi> for want of proviſion, ſo as that the water ſhould never have bin <hi>ſcant</hi> or <hi>bitter;</hi> yea that they ſhould never have <hi>met</hi> with an <hi>enemy;</hi> theſe and all other hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips the Lord could have prevented: But he did <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſuffer</hi> theſe intricate abſtruſe difficulties to fall in,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112329:16"/>for the <hi>proving</hi> of his people, for ſo it followes in the 16. verſe of the ſame chapter, <hi>He fed thee with Manna in the wilderneſſe, which thy fathers knew not, that he might humble thee, and that he might</hi> PROVE <hi>thee:</hi> Not but that <hi>he knew</hi> their hearts, but becauſe <hi>they knew not</hi> their owne hearts, much leſſe did others know their ſpirits. Alas how few of us did know our <hi>owne hearts</hi> whilſt we lived in peace and proſperity in our countries and callings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Lord by the <hi>intricateneſſe</hi> of theſe carriages, and by the mazes of his proceedings did <hi>pumpe-up</hi> and <hi>draw forth</hi> our inward parts! Thus <hi>humbling, proving, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved,</hi> and <hi>engaging,</hi> were the Lords foure <hi>grand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes</hi> upon Iſrael: And upon the ſame grounds did he lead <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> at their firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a ſtrange country, by extraordinary providence, to prove, and improve their graces; yea and to <hi>diet</hi> them and <hi>breath</hi> them (as it were) for greater mercies and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. And I am perſwaded that by that time God hath <hi>brought together</hi> both ends of this myſterious ſalvation that he is now working, every ſerious chriſtian amongſt us ſhall be able to ſay, that he <hi>could not</hi> have <hi>beene with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> any one of all thoſe obſtructions and afflictions that we have met withall: Nay I am perſwaded that we ſhall all freely conclude at laſt, that if we had not <hi>loſt all,</hi> we had bin <hi>undone;</hi> if we had not beene <hi>plundred,</hi> we had beene <hi>beggerd;</hi> if all theſe myſterious abſtruſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties had not fallen in, we never had ſeene halfe ſo much of <hi>God,</hi> of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> or <hi>ſin, reformation,</hi> as I hope we ſhall now diſcerne. But I haſten,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A third ground,</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin" type="runSum">For the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies greater confuſion.</note> why God delights thus to carry on his great ſalvations; and eſpecially, his Babyloniſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, is for the <hi>enemies greater confuſion;</hi> either of their <hi>faces,</hi> or <hi>perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112329:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> for the greater confuſion of their <hi>faces,</hi> when God having put them in hope of winning the day,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of their Faces.</note> ſhall <hi>out-reach</hi> and out-do them at laſt; when the Lord ſhall ſo <hi>befoole them,</hi> that in the concluſion they ſhall ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>wiped out</hi> of all their hopes, this will be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their greater ſhame and confuſion of <hi>face:</hi> When an <hi>oraculous Achitophel</hi> ſhall find his counſell over-reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>a plaine Huſhai,</hi> that is the next way to make him become <hi>his own hangman:</hi> When an <hi>inſolent Haman</hi> ſhal ſee himſelfe degraded by a modeſt godly <hi>female Esther,</hi> it is the way to make him <hi>fall downe</hi> upon the <hi>bed,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to wiſh himſelfe <hi>diſpatched</hi> upon his owne <hi>Gibbet:</hi> When a <hi>Siſera,</hi> a triumphant <hi>Siſera,</hi> ſhall be nailed to the ground by the hand of a <hi>Jael:</hi> When a <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and an <hi>Herod</hi> ſhall be beaten and eaten with <hi>lice,</hi> ſo that they ſhall be faine to ſtand ſhrugging and picking like a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in a buſh, Oh what <hi>confuſion</hi> of <hi>face</hi> muſt this needs be, not only upon the perſons themſelves that do ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, but upon all their <hi>Tribe</hi> and adherents? What groſſe <hi>confuſion of face</hi> (gueſſe we with our ſelves) was there to <hi>Sanballat, Tobiah, Geſhem</hi> and the reſt, when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their ſecret <hi>fraud</hi> and open <hi>force,</hi> after all their letters and machinations to hinder the building of the <hi>Temple,</hi> yet the worke was perfected at laſt? You ſhall reade in <hi>Nehemiah</hi> (Chap. 6. verſ. 15.) that <hi>the wall was finiſhed in the</hi> 25. <hi>day of the month Elul in fifty and two dayes,</hi> ſo that all their paines, charge and diligence came ſhort, both their <hi>toyle</hi> and <hi>oyle</hi> was loſt: Therupon, (in the 16. verſe) ſaith the Text, <hi>It came to paſſe that when all our enemies heard thereof, and all the Heathen that were about us ſaw theſe things, they were much caſt downe in their owne eyes,</hi> that is, they knew not which way to <hi>looke,</hi> nor where to beſtow their faces, but ſtood like ſo many <hi>theeves</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112329:17"/>in the very act, caſting their eies towards the ground.</p>
            <p>O doe but gueſſe with your ſelves, doe but <hi>gueſſe</hi> with your ſelves, Honourable and beloved, when God ſhall bring about this preſent myſterious work of his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and put a glorious iſſue unto it, (for this worke <hi>must</hi> have a glorious iſſue) I ſay it again in ſhort, when at the end of theſe troubles the worldly and wicked <hi>Politicians</hi> ſhall find themſelves <hi>out-witted,</hi> the <hi>Potentates over-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> and the <hi>wealthy</hi> men <hi>out-purſed,</hi> and that all this ſhall be done by thoſe whom they accounted meer <hi>fooliſhneſſe, weakneſſe,</hi> and <hi>poverty;</hi> then, then doe but gueſſe with your ſelves how will the moſt active, induſtrious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent enemies be able to <hi>lift up their fereheads?</hi> How will they look upon one another? Surely juſt like a <hi>ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> of hungry <hi>Curs</hi> that all the day have been hotly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing their prey or game, and at night have miſt and <hi>lost</hi> it in a <hi>wood.</hi> I cannot but think with my ſelfe that it will be <hi>worth</hi> all the paines and coſt that an active man ſhall lay out in this work, but to ſee that <hi>Babel,</hi> that confuſion of <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>faces,</hi> that will befall the enemies at laſt. A <hi>ſhadow</hi> of this confuſion of face and language you find propheſied in <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. verſ. 15, 16, 17. <hi>The Merchants which were made rich by her, ſhall ſtand afarre off, weeping and wailing, and ſaying, Alas, alas, that great City that was clothed in fine linnen, and purple, and ſcarlet, and decked with gold and precious ſtones, and pearles, for in one houre ſo great riches is come to nought.</hi> And verſ. 19. <hi>They</hi> (that is, the <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth, the <hi>Merchants,</hi> the <hi>Ship-masters,</hi> and <hi>ſaylers) caſt dust on their heads and cryed, weeping and wailing, ſaying, Alas, alas, that great City wherein were made rich all that had ſhips in the ſea by reaſon of her coſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for in one houre ſhe is made deſolate.</hi> Thus God doth it for the greater confuſion of the faces of his enemies.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:112329:17"/>
            <p>Or, ſecondly, if they want ſo much modeſty as to be capable of confuſion of face,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> yet theſe hidden carriages ſhall work for the <hi>greater confuſion</hi> of their <hi>perſons:</hi> they ſhal be the more utterly confounded by theſe myſteries. If the <hi>men</hi> of the <hi>old world</hi> will be ſo impudently wicked, as not to bluſh at <hi>Noahs</hi> preaching &amp; building, they ſhal wade <hi>knee-deep</hi> in the floud to begge admiſſion into the Arke, but not obtaine it. If the <hi>King of Egypt</hi> and all his Gipſies will be ſo ſhameleſſe as to dodge ten times with the Lord, they ſhall at laſt <hi>cry and fly</hi> againſt the return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeas, and all in vaine, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.26. So that all the <hi>Meanders</hi> and intricate carriages of the work until then, did but ripen them for greater perſonall confuſion: Had <hi>Pharaoh</hi> come in upon the firſt ſummons (the firſt mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle) or upon the ſecond or third, the man might have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his life, and perchance his Kingdom; but therfore the Lord will ſuffer him to be baited on with a kind of viciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitude of loſſes and victories, that all this might <hi>harden</hi> his heart, and the hearts of all his Magicians, deſperately to <hi>plunge themſelves</hi> into the bottome of the ſea, where they might be <hi>ſlain</hi> and <hi>buried</hi> at once.</p>
            <p>This very ground <hi>[for the enemies greater deſtruction]</hi> is hinted in <hi>this</hi> ſame <hi>Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie</hi> of <hi>Eſay,</hi> chap. 44. ver. 25. Saith hee, <hi>Hee fru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trateth the tokens of the lyars, and maketh diviners mad, he turneth wiſemen backward, and maketh their knowledge fooliſh.</hi> Marke, hee carrieth his worke ſo myſteriouſly, that hee might <hi>frustrate the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of the lyars,</hi> that is, of thoſe that were ſo confident upon ſome poore petty ſucceſſes and victories which they had obtained againſt the people of God, that (ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon) they durſt <hi>to divine,</hi> and promiſe unto their party a totall, finall, ſpeedy <hi>conquest.</hi> Now when God ſhall <hi>turne all</hi> about again, in a time, in a way, where they loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112329:18"/>not for it, doubtleſſe ſuch a ſtrange <hi>ſurpriſall</hi> wil put them into the condition of the men of <hi>Ai</hi> when they were encompaſſed by <hi>Ioſhua's Stratagem, Ioſh.</hi> 8.20. <hi>They had no power to flee this way or that way,</hi> verſ. 22. <hi>They were in the midst of Iſrael, ſome on this ſide, and ſome on that ſide, and they ſmote them ſo that they let none of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine or eſcape:</hi> And all this was done by a Stratagem, for before in verſ. 15. <hi>Ioſhua and all Iſrael made as if they were beaten before them</hi> (of Ai) <hi>and fied by the way of the wilderneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee it is <hi>a neceſſary</hi> and <hi>rationall</hi> truth, that the Lord doth thus carry-on his great ſalvations, <hi>viz.</hi> for his owne greater glory, for his peoples greater benefit, and for his enemies greater confuſion: Therefore it is not out of <hi>want</hi> either of power or wiſdome, but out of <hi>a tranſcendency</hi> of both that he doth order his deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in ſuch a manner. So much may demonſtrate the <hi>Theſis</hi> or generall part. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, if you demand a particular <hi>reaſon</hi> for the <hi>Hypotheſis, viz.</hi> Why <hi>ſalvations from Babylon</hi> are alſo carried in a myſtery? I anſwer, that there is a <hi>ſpeciall ground</hi> for this branch alſo. And it is this in ſhort.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Babylon</hi> (I meane the <hi>westerne</hi>) was <hi>rayſed</hi> in a <hi>myſtery,</hi> and therefore it is good reaſon that it ſhould be throwne downe in the <hi>ſame manner.</hi> In the 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.6. You ſhall find that <hi>Babylon</hi> is built up in a myſtery; <hi>The myſtery of iniquity doth already worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>noble Frenchman</hi> throughout his Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<note place="margin">Mornaei Myſterium Iniquitatis.</note> gives us a ſufficient commentary upon this text, by diſcovering the parts of that myſtery, ſhewing the <hi>Pede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and how he hath gathered his <hi>ſtoln fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> together, of which when every bird ſhall take his owne, he ſhall be left naked and bare.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:112329:18"/>
            <p>Alſo in Revel. 17.4.5.6. You ſhall ſee that Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon was raiſed in a myſtery. <hi>And the woman was arayed in purple and ſcarlet colour, and decked with gold and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, having a golden cup in her hand, full of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and filthineſſe of her fornication.</hi> This <hi>woman</hi> is <hi>Rome,</hi> the weſtern Babylon: <hi>And upon her forehead was a name written</hi> in Capitall Letters, <hi>Myſtery, Babylon the great, the mother of harlots, and abominations of the earth.</hi> Called <hi>[Myſtery]</hi> becauſe ſhe was <hi>rayſed</hi> in a <hi>myſtery;</hi> that is, ſhe got up to her height inſenſibly, cunningly; her way in getting up was like the way of an <hi>Eagle</hi> in the <hi>ayre,</hi> or like the way of a <hi>ſerpent</hi> upon a <hi>ſtone,</hi> winding, and ſcruing it ſelfe onwards by degrees; untraceably; or as the way of a <hi>ſhip</hi> in the <hi>ſea,</hi> which goeth on ſwiftly when ſhe ſeemes to ſtand ſtill. Thus Babylon was ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and built in a myſtery, and therefore it is but juſt and <hi>proportionable</hi> that ſhe ſhould be caſt downe and ruined in a myſtery.</p>
            <p>Nay we have an hint, yea a <hi>prophetique command</hi> that this proportion ſhall be obſerved in the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this Babylon in Revel. 18.6. <hi>Reward her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as ſhe rewarded you,</hi> and <hi>double unto her double accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her workes:</hi> And verſe 7. <hi>How much ſhe hath glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified her ſelfe and lived deliciouſly, ſo much ſorrow and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment give her;</hi> that is, let her be caſt downe by the ſame ſteps by which ſhe climb'd up, both for manner and meaſure.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee grounds for the generall and alſo for the particular,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Application.</note> why Gods great ſalvations of his people and eſpecially from Babylon, are, ſhall be, muſt be ſo my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriouſly carried on. The <hi>Application</hi> is the great <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> in which I am ſent at this time.
<note n="1" place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 1. Enquirie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Are the Lords great ſalvations of his people eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112329:19"/>from Babylon, carried-on in a myſtery? Then my firſt doſe or <hi>portion</hi> ſhall be meerly <hi>preparatory.</hi> Let us make <hi>Engliſh</hi> of this text, by <hi>enquiring</hi> and <hi>ſearching</hi> whether or no the <hi>preſent</hi> great worke of ſalvation and reformation that is in <hi>your hands</hi> (for 'tis a worke of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation) be carryed-on in a myſtery? What? is it a plain worke of <hi>common providence</hi> in which ordinary cauſes do bring forth their wonted effects and iſſues, <hi>without</hi> any remarkeable <hi>variation?</hi> or rather, is it not an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, elaborate, <hi>ſhadowed Maſter-piece,</hi> altogether made up of Stratagems, Paradoxes, and Wonders? If thus, then comfort your ſelves, you may <hi>conclude</hi> it will be a great <hi>ſalvation,</hi> yea (as I ſhall ſhew) a ſalvation from Babylon. So then, the whole buſineſſe of this preparatory uſe will be to enquire and <hi>imforme</hi> our ſelves diſtinctly and <hi>critically</hi> in this great queſtion <hi>[when is a ſalvation carryed-on in a myſtery?</hi> or, how may I know ſuch a worke?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.2. <hi>the works of the Lord are great;</hi> yet they may be <hi>ſought out</hi> of all them that have pleaſure therein. I ſhall endeavour for our direction and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, in theſe troublous times, to give ſome ſpeciall <hi>evidences</hi> of an <hi>[hiding Saviour]</hi> that is of a great, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh, myſterious redemption.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt when the work is carryed on SPIRITUALLY: This I ſhall call <hi>[ſupra Naturam]</hi> above nature.</item>
               <item>2. When, CASUALLY; which is <hi>[preter naturam]</hi> beſides nature.</item>
               <item>3. When, CONTRARILY and CONTRADICTORILY <hi>[contra naturam]</hi> even againſt nature.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt when a work is carryed on <hi>Supra naturam</hi> [SPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITUALLY] that is,
<note n="1" place="margin" type="runSum">Spiritually.</note> more by ſpirituall than by fleſhly meanes. Thus we reade of the Jewiſh redemption from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112329:19"/>Babylon, Zecha. 4.6. <hi>Then he</hi> (that is, the Angel) <hi>ſpeake and ſaid, This is the word of the Lord unto Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel, ſaying, Not by might,</hi> or armes, <hi>nor by power, but by my</hi> SPIRIT <hi>ſaith the Lord of Hosts. Who art thou,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>O great mountaine?</hi> It was a <hi>mountaine of rubbiſh</hi> that lay there (as ſome conceive) being the ruines of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Temple, as <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4. verſe 2. and 10. This moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine muſt be removed ere the ground could be levelled for a foundation: But how ſhall this be done? Not by might, nor by power, but he ſhall bring forth the <hi>corner ſtone</hi> thereof, with <hi>ſhoutings,</hi> crying <hi>Grace, grace</hi> unto it. It ſhould be done <hi>without hands,</hi> only by the word of the Lords mouth, as the Earth and Heavens were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But in <hi>Hag.</hi> 4. verſ. 14. You ſhall finde a <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſtirring</hi> of ſpirits that carryed on that work: <hi>And the Lord ſtirred up the ſpirit of Zerubbabel</hi> (it was an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate working upon his ſpirit, which neither man or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils are able to reach) <hi>the ſon of Shealtiel, governor of Iudah; and the ſpirit of Joſuah, the ſon of Joſedech the high Prieſt &amp; the ſpirit of al the remnant of the people.</hi> God moved the ſpirit of the temporall rulers, of <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> that is as it were the <hi>Parliament;</hi> God moved the ſpirit of thoſe of the Church, of <hi>Joſuah</hi> the high Prieſt, and of <hi>Haggai,</hi> and <hi>Zechariah</hi> the Prophets, as it were the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines;</hi> and God moved the ſpirit of all the <hi>remnant</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> (the whole <hi>commonalty</hi>) &amp; they <hi>came &amp; did work in the houſe of the Lord of Hosts their God:</hi> It ſeemes it was not for <hi>wages</hi> or out of any <hi>conſtraint,</hi> but only becauſe the Lord had <hi>touched</hi> their ſpirits and inclined their hearts to this ſervice. So it is ſaid of <hi>Cyrus</hi> in <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.1. <hi>The Lord ſtirred up the ſpirit of Cyrus King of Perſia,</hi> he gave the Jewes leave to build, and did affiſt them, and ſupply them with neceſſaries for the ſervice. And Chap. 5.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112329:20"/>verſe 1. <hi>The Prophets, Haggai and Zechariah the ſon of Iddo, propheſied unto the Jewes that were in Judah and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem in the name of the God of Iſrael, even unto them: Then,</hi> verſe 2. <hi>roſe up Zerubbabel the ſon of Shealtiel and Ieſhua the ſon of Iozadek, and began to build the houſe of God.</hi> Why, what moved them at <hi>that time</hi> above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Onely the <hi>Miniſters preached</hi> them about the worke: As before I ſhewed that the wals of <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt be <hi>preached down,</hi> ſo it ſeemes here that the walls of the <hi>Temple</hi> muſt be <hi>preached up. Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zachariah</hi> doe fall to preaching, and then the rulers and the people doe fall to building.</p>
            <p>How <hi>parallell</hi> is our caſe with this? Hath <hi>might</hi> or <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> fleſh or ſpirit, (I aske of your own conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) had the greateſt ſtroake in our greateſt ſalvations hitherto? Have not the <hi>touched hearts,</hi> the willing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ever bin the chief inſtruments? Is it not moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the Lord hath <hi>toucht</hi> ſome hearts with the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>wisdome</hi> and counſell, as ſometime he touched the heart of <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi> filling them with his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>in knowledge &amp;c. to deviſe cunning workes, to work in gold and in ſilver &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 31.2. ſo <hi>amongſt us</hi> hath he not given an extraordinary <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>counſell</hi> and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into the hearts of men, even then when 'twas feared that diſuſe and oppreſſion had quite <hi>worne out</hi> all the <hi>old race</hi> of true Engliſh hearts? Who had thought we had bin ſo rich in Parliamentary ſpirits, as appears this day?</p>
            <p>Againe, others have beene as it were inſpired with a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>courage</hi> and magnanimity beyond preſident, and even unto their own admiration. Yea ſome like that <hi>Fabius,</hi> or like <hi>Gideon</hi> in the ſtory before, have bin called off from meane imployments; and yet have anſwered great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112329:20"/>expectations in the ſervices of warre: ſo that I cannot but gueſſe that ſucceeding generations writing the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of theſe times will ſpeake rather of a <hi>Creation</hi> than of a <hi>Generation</hi> of ſouldiers in our age.</p>
            <p>Once more; How many Nobles, Gentry, Miniſters, and people, every where are ſuddenly ſprung up like <hi>Jonah</hi> his <hi>gourd</hi> againſt this hot ſeaſon? men accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo many graces, gifts, qualifications, for this work, as if they had bin inſpired, <hi>cut out</hi> and <hi>created</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for this ſervice? Beleeve it, theſe are things that deſerve a moſt ſerious conſideration, they do prove that the worke is carryed-on ſpiritually. But that is not all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Salvation is then carryed on in a myſtery when it is carryed on [PRAETER NATURAM] I Engliſh it [CASUALLY] or accidentally; that is, thorow a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of extraordinary accidents and caſualties. By <hi>caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties</hi> I do not meane the acts or effects of Pagan fortune, but the acts and effects of extraordinary and <hi>ſpeciall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence;</hi> when there is a frequent confluence of ſuch acts appearing in our ſalvations, this muſt needs be <hi>beſides</hi> natures rode; for <hi>Quae caſu fiunt ea rare fiunt,</hi> that is, <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties</hi> are <hi>rarities,</hi> ſaith the heathen, or, things done by chance are ſeldome done. Now when we ſhall ſee ſuch events fall in frequently, then we muſt conclude that the finger of God is there, this is not according to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> rule and <hi>rode</hi> of men.</p>
            <p>That you may underſtand my meaning a little more fully in this particular, I will give you an <hi>inſtance</hi> of this <hi>confluence of caſualties</hi> in the booke and <hi>caſe</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſther,</hi> Chapter 6. When <hi>Haman</hi> had <hi>made ſure</hi> with King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> (that is, <hi>Xerxes</hi>) for the utter extirpation of the Jewes, and that <hi>Eſther</hi> had now begun another Mine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112329:21"/>to <hi>counter-worke</hi> him, ſee what a heape, what a cluſter of ſeaſonable caſuall circumſtances do happily fall in for the advantage of <hi>Eſther,</hi> and the diſadvantage of <hi>Haman.</hi> Thus in ſhort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> in verſe 1. It is ſaid that <hi>[on that night could not the King ſleepe]</hi> What night was that? Juſt the next night before that <hi>Eſther</hi> ſtood engaged to break <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai's</hi> matter to the King upon the morrow, Chap. 5. verſ. 8. the very night before that day, the King could not ſleepe: And it was alſo juſt the night before that <hi>Haman</hi> meant to beg the execution of <hi>Mordecai.</hi> The night im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly before that theſe <hi>two things</hi> were to be ſet on worke, the King <hi>could not ſleepe:</hi> why, what ayled him? we heare of no extraordinary <hi>ſad tydings</hi> which were brought him that could hinder his ſleepe; we reade of <hi>no diſtemper</hi> of body that lay upon him; then doubtleſſe <hi>Gods hand</hi> was in it, therefore he could not ſleepe. But that is not all.</p>
            <p>Thereupon <hi>(ſecondly)</hi> he <hi>commanded to bring the booke of Records of the Chronicls to be read before him.</hi> True, we ſay <hi>reading</hi> and preaching will <hi>bring men aſleepe</hi> though they have little diſpoſition to it before: but al this could not incline him to ſlumber. This farther ſhewes the hand of God.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>thirdly,</hi> It was <hi>found written in the Booke, that Mordecai had done a choyce peece</hi> of ſervice for the King: <hi>Found,</hi> how was it ſound? How did it come to hand? did the <hi>Reader</hi> willingly <hi>turne</hi> to this place that ſo he might make way to ingratiate <hi>Mordecai?</hi> That is improbable, becauſe <hi>Haman</hi> that was now the darling of the Court, was <hi>Mordecaies</hi> knowne and profeſt <hi>enemy:</hi> Or, what did the <hi>King command</hi> that he ſhould turne to that place? No, that is not probable neither; becauſe we find by the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112329:21"/>
               <hi>Kings</hi> next queſtion that he did <hi>not know</hi> to the contrary but that <hi>Mordecai</hi> had bin already rewarded for this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. How then came this about? Surely, that very <hi>God</hi> that directed the <hi>Eunuch</hi> when <hi>Philip</hi> joyned himſelfe unto his Charet to be reading that place of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. And that <hi>voice</hi> that cryed to the Father <hi>Tolle &amp; lege, take up and reade,</hi> it ſeems that very <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> did direct, that amongſt all ſorts of <hi>bookes</hi> the King ſhould pitch upon <hi>History,</hi> and amongſt all ſorts of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory <hi>this volume,</hi> and amongſt all the parts of this vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, <hi>this page,</hi> this paſſage, that ſo way might be made for <hi>Esthers</hi> intended motion.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>fourthly,</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>And the King</hi> SAID, <hi>what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignity hath been done to Mordecai for this?</hi> Why did the King <hi>take notice</hi> of this ſervice at this time more then formerly; for it is ſaid, chap. 2. ver. 22. that <hi>Esther</hi> had (formerly) <hi>certified the King</hi> of this buſineſſe in <hi>Mordecai's</hi> name, yet then no reward is thought upon? But it ſeemes <hi>Mordecai's reward</hi> was <hi>kept</hi> for this very time by an act of extraordinary providence.</p>
            <p>But <hi>fifthly</hi> (to put a heape of caſualties together) That, <hi>Haman</hi> ſhould ſo ſeaſonably <hi>come in,</hi> in that very nick of time when <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> was ſtudying how to reward <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai.</hi> That, <hi>Haman</hi> ſhould come in with <hi>that request</hi> and motion for the executing of <hi>Mordecai.</hi> Adde to theſe, the Kings <hi>admiſsion</hi> of <hi>Haman;</hi> the <hi>queſtion</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him; and <hi>Hamans anſwer</hi> to that queſtion, all which you may reade in chap. 6. verſ. 4, 5, 6. And then all <hi>theſe graines</hi> put together do make a great <hi>weight;</hi> Let all theſe caſuall circumſtances be caſt in, and you muſt confeſſe that every particular of them being a ſeverall piece of wonder, the whole doth make up little leſſe than <hi>a Miracle.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:112329:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Honourable and beloved,</hi> how eaſily could I ſhew you the <hi>faces</hi> of ſuch like caſualties, or <hi>petty-wonders,</hi> in the glaſſe of your <hi>owne</hi> proceedings? You have inſtances enough of your owne (I meane in your <hi>owne History)</hi> to parallel all theſe particulars and a thouſand more; I need not to go <hi>a borrowing</hi> for you. Only thus much in a word, this <hi>Manna</hi> of rarities from heaven, is your <hi>daily bread.</hi> I muſt on-wards.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a work is then carried-on myſteriouſly, when it is carried on <hi>[contra naturam.]</hi> What Engliſh ſhall I have to reach this expreſſion withall? When a worke is carried on CONTRARILY and CONTRADICTORILY: It is an hard phraſe, but ſo <hi>over-flowing</hi> are the myſteries of mercy, which God is now working amongſt us, that certainly our Engliſh tongue is grown <hi>too narrow</hi> to lend us words to expreſſe them. I muſt therefore uſe the word <hi>Contradictorily.</hi> Contradictory, what is that? That is, when a worke is promoted and carried-on by its <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> I muſt ſhew it by an inſtance. When the carriage of a worke doth run like <hi>Samſons</hi> riddle, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Out of the Eater came forth meat, and out of the ſtrong ſweetneſſe.</hi> That the <hi>Eater</hi> ſhould yeeld <hi>meat,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrong</hi> give out <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> this is ſuch a riddle that a ſtrict <hi>Logician</hi> hearing it would be ready to cry out-<hi>Implicat,</hi> 'tis a contradiction <hi>in adjecto;</hi> yet ſo it is when <hi>enemies</hi> do become <hi>furtherers</hi> of a worke <hi>against themſelves,</hi> and that is common you ſee amongſt us.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Samſons</hi> riddle doth not expreſſe it ſufficiently, adde another expreſſion out of the Pſalmiſt; It is in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 112.4. <hi>Unto the upright there ariſeth light in darkneſſe.</hi> It is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to nature that the <hi>dawning</hi> doth ſpring out of the <hi>night,</hi> and that the more <hi>perfect day</hi> doth ariſe out of that <hi>dawning</hi> is ſtill according to nature, becauſe the increaſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112329:22"/>is <hi>graduall:</hi> But when <hi>light</hi> ſhall ariſe <hi>immediatly</hi> out of <hi>darkneſſe;</hi> when <hi>high-noone</hi> ſhall ſuddenly leape out of <hi>midnight,</hi> ſuch a jumpe is againſt nature, and you muſt call it a myſtery; becauſe it is held as a <hi>Maxim</hi> amongſt <hi>Naturaliſts,</hi> that <hi>Natura nihil agit per ſaltum,</hi> the motion of nature is not by leaps, but by paces. Thus <hi>Mark.</hi> 4.28. <hi>First the blade, then the eare, after that the full corne in the eare.</hi> Therefore as often as we ſhall ſee a <hi>branch</hi> (I meane a fruit of Providence) like the <hi>Rod of Aaron,</hi> that in <hi>one night</hi> was budded and brought forth <hi>buds</hi> and bloomed <hi>bloſſomes,</hi> and yeelded <hi>Almonds (Numb.</hi> 17.8.) ſo often let us confeſſe with the <hi>Pſalmist, This is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, but when, or where did we ever ſee ſuch things as theſe?</p>
            <p>I would give ſome few particular <hi>inſtances</hi> under this head of ſalvation through <hi>contrarieties</hi> and <hi>contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> As</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin" type="runSum">Enemies furtherers.</note> When <hi>Enemies</hi> doe <hi>further</hi> a <hi>worke</hi> againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yea and that by fighting againſt it. This contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction we have found true ever ſince the beginning of our preſent troubles. The <hi>enemy</hi> by projecting &amp; fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt Reformation, hath both haſtened and hight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it <hi>more then our ſelves</hi> could (perhaps would) have done in that time. When there had been a talke a while after the beginning of this Parliament, of ſome ſolemne way of uniting the Kingdomes by ſome ſpeciall <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in thoſe crazie times; the enemy by increaſing our dangers and obſtructing (as I remember) the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, do <hi>quicken</hi> us into a <hi>Proteſtation:</hi> And becauſe that obligation was eaſily broken (ah lamentable!) by the generality of men who deſerted their owne protection and remedy, therefore the enemy would never leave ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112329:23"/>one horrid provocation to another, by fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, denying them a being, proclaiming them Rebels, and owning the Diabolicall Rebels of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as good Subjects, to cut their throats; untill by ſuch ſharp provocations as theſe, they had <hi>ſpur'd</hi> and ſwitch'd the three Kingdomes into a moſt <hi>Solemne Oath and Covenant</hi> for a compleat Reformation. The men <hi>would not ſuffer us</hi> (if we would) only to pare and <hi>clip Prelacy,</hi> no, they will have it pluckd up <hi>Roote &amp; Branch.</hi> They will not ſuffer the three Kingdomes to reſt in ſeverall kinds and pitches of government and worſhip, but they will have one true <hi>reformed uniformity</hi> in theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches of Chriſt. Thus their rage hath abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly <hi>ripened</hi> the worke. This is ſeemingly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When one and the <hi>ſame thing</hi> is at once <hi>helpfull</hi> to Gods people,
<note n="2" place="margin" type="runSum">Helpfull-Hurt.</note> and <hi>hurtfull</hi> to the enemy. As it is ſayd of the <hi>Angel,</hi> and of the Pillar of the <hi>Cloude,</hi> Exod 14.19. <hi>And the Angel of God which went before the Camp of Iſrael, removed and went behinde them, and the Pillar of the cloud went from before their faces and ſtood behind them.</hi> ver. 20. <hi>And it came between the Campe of the Egyptians, and the Campe of Iſrael, and it was a cloude of darkneſſe to them, but it gave light by night to theſe, ſo that the one came not neer the other all the night.</hi> Such <hi>helpfull-hindering</hi> occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents have we often met withall, that have proved like the <hi>extraordinary froſt</hi> that ('tis ſaid) did ſuddenly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in the North at the comming in of the preſent <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Army; it <hi>blocked up</hi> the wayes of the <hi>enemy</hi> by abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>Snow,</hi> that they could not plunder and fire as they intended; but it gave an unexpected <hi>paſſage</hi> of <hi>Ice</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the river unto our <hi>Brethren</hi> and their carriages. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny like acts might be ſhewen, which upon the one hand
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112329:23"/>did ſhew the <hi>Lords preſence</hi> with his people, (as I have ſeen ſome <hi>two faced</hi> pictures) and on the other hand in the ſame ſide the picture of <hi>Satan</hi> for the ruine of the enemies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When <hi>leſſes</hi> are <hi>gaines.</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin" type="runSum">Loſſes Gains</note> I have touched upon this before; let me only adde the inſtances of the two great <hi>Publique Battels</hi> that have been fought in this <hi>Cauſe,</hi> at <hi>Keinton</hi> and at <hi>Newbery.</hi> In the <hi>beginning</hi> of both bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, tis ſaid, we were ſomewhat <hi>worſted,</hi> to ſhew that <hi>England</hi> had offended the Lord, and therefore our Father did beat us: But then we <hi>conquered</hi> the enemy too, to imply that the Lord would owne his owne Cauſe and people notwithſtanding their failings. Thus <hi>victi vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> by being firſt worſted, we were made <hi>more</hi> than <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours [Periiſſemus niſi periiſſemus]</hi> being beaten wee got the day. This Examination is preparatory to the following leſſons.</p>
            <p>Uſe 2. To <hi>informe and ſatisfie.</hi> Let no man think it <hi>ſtrange</hi> that there is <hi>ſo much ſhrinking,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 2. To informe and ſatisfie.</note> ſtretching and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from the right Party in the preſent times and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies. No marvell if meer <hi>Senſitive</hi> common <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> and carnall <hi>Politicians</hi> do fall off from this Divine and Supernaturall Cauſe and taske. Such poore <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind</hi> creatures were miſtaken in this worke at their firſt comming on. It was thier <hi>lot to be caſt upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſide;</hi> and in that lot, they did looke upon carnall and <hi>ſelviſh</hi> ends and arguments; upon the <hi>leaves</hi> and the <hi>bagg</hi> that were to be gotten by Chriſts ſervice, I meane majority of <hi>number,</hi> probability of ſhort <hi>diſpatch</hi> and long <hi>preferments</hi> after, did draw them to the right par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But <hi>finding</hi> the buſineſſe to be an <hi>holy myſtery,</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Lord did carry his worke thorow hills and dales of Land and Seas; yea and that they ſhould be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112329:24"/>forced to deny themſelves, to adventure all, to croſſe the ſtreame, &amp;c. Here they <hi>went away ſorrowing,</hi> this was too hard a ſaying, they could not beare it. To ſpeak plainly: Honourable and Beloved, in the <hi>beginning</hi> of this <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> when the Lord did give you a plentifull <hi>Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt</hi> of moſt ſmooth and happy ſucceſſe in your firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, thereby to ſtrengthen you for the hard <hi>dayes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke</hi> and long journey that was to come, (as he gave a <hi>double breakfast</hi> to <hi>Elijah</hi> when he was to travell without meat <hi>forty dayes and forty nights, unto Horeb the Mount of God,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.5, 7, 8.) You may remember that in thoſe proſperous dayes you were compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with <hi>ſwarming Proſelytes,</hi> and ſeeming Patriots of all bores and ſizes: But how did many of thoſe Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders faile you in the heat as <hi>brookes in Summer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of them were meere <hi>ſenſitive</hi> friends;
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Senſitive friends.</note> Theſe like incredulous <hi>Thomas,</hi> would beleeve and adventure no farther than their <hi>ſenſes</hi> (of ſight and feeling) did lead them. They would have the ground of their faith at their <hi>fingers-end,</hi> as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.25. and they were drawn on meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as that <hi>mixed multitude</hi> (or a great mixture) that went out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with the children of Iſrael, becauſe of the <hi>miracles</hi> and mercies that there were wrought, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.38. And therefore anon after when your hardſhips be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, this ſame mixture were the firſt that <hi>fell to luſting,</hi> as that Egyptian mixture did, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.4. <hi>And the mixed multitude that was among them fell to luſting, &amp;c.</hi> Thus your meere ſenſitive friends did fall off.</p>
            <p>Others were led by <hi>human reaſon</hi> and politique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions;
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Meere poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticians.</note> Theſe did ſtick to Parliaments, Laws and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, as <hi>Orpah</hi> to her mother in law <hi>Naomi,</hi> that is, whilſt ſhe continued <hi>Naomi (pleaſant)</hi> but when by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions ſhe became <hi>Marah (bitter)</hi> then they (as <hi>Orpah,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112329:24"/>Ruth</hi> 1.14.20.) <hi>wept and kiſſed their mother in law, but departed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shortly,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Falſe and faint Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</note> a <hi>last ſort</hi> were of falſe or <hi>faint-hearted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours,</hi> led with ſome light of Religion; they either brake-off like <hi>Demas,</hi> or warped-off like <hi>Paul's acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> at his firſt appearing before <hi>Nero,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>But would you know the cauſe of all this failing? Surely it was nothing but this (as before) thoſe ſhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed narrow-hearted <hi>carnalists</hi> were <hi>puzled</hi> in this hard leſſon of a <hi>Mystery.</hi> The meere <hi>naturall man</hi> can reade in the <hi>booke</hi> of the <hi>creatures,</hi> 'tis ſo faire a print in <hi>Capitall letters.</hi> The <hi>Prudentiall</hi> man can perceive the <hi>character,</hi> and conſtrue the <hi>language</hi> of <hi>common providence:</hi> And thus far they went with you: But they were not ſo much as, <hi>A-b-c-ederians</hi> in the Lords <hi>Archivis</hi> (as they ſay) in his <hi>Manuſcripts,</hi> in his <hi>Brachigraphy,</hi> I meane in the ſtrange language and abſtruſe character of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and myſterious Babyloniſh redemptions; they wanted both <hi>Dictionaries</hi> and <hi>Spectacles</hi> in thoſe particulars. Then let not the apoſtacie of carnaliſts caſt any diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement upon this glorious Myſtery. That's a ſecond Uſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if Gods great ſalvations, of his people, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that from Babylon be carryed-on in a myſterie,
<note n="3" place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 3. Reproofe of carnality. Both.</note> then <hi>away with</hi> that great <hi>old Engliſh</hi> ſin of <hi>Carnallity,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with Carnality in <hi>both extreames,</hi> upon the right hand, and upon the left hand, away with <hi>carnall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and <hi>carnall diffidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, away with <hi>carnall confidence;</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</note> Be not too much lifted up with outward ſupplies, with outward ſtrength and ſucceſſes; but remember that the frame of this work is myſterious and ſpirituall; therfore for us to build our hopes upon things that are meerly carnall, muſt needs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112329:25"/>be <hi>a ſin,</hi> both <hi>heterogeneous</hi> and moſt improper. We have bin taught by experience, that fleſhly and <hi>worldly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages</hi> hitherto have contributed <hi>little</hi> to the principale part of this worke. Commonly (hitherto) <hi>the race hath not been to the ſwift, nor the battell to the ſtrong, nor yet bread to men of underſtanding, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.11. We never had (I thinke) <hi>too few</hi> Armies for any ſervice and ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſince we began; perhaps ſometimes through the corruption of our hearts we have had <hi>too many,</hi> as God ſayd unto <hi>Gideon, The people that are with thee are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for me to give the Midianites into their hands.</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der farther, that carnall confidence <hi>begets</hi> carnall diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as the hot and cold <hi>fits</hi> in an <hi>Aguiſh-fever</hi> doe mutually intend and heighten one another. Therefore away with carnality upon the right hand, with carnall confidence.</p>
            <p>And then on the other hand,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Carnal dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</note> by the ſame reaſon, away alſo with <hi>carnall diffidence</hi> in caſe of the want of outward ſupplies and ſucceſſes: Remember the Doctrine, that hath ſaid that this worke is a worke <hi>of faith,</hi> and not of ſenſe; and continuall experience doth evidence that <hi>when we are weak we are ſtrong:</hi> My meaning is, that we ſhould not be any longer like <hi>weather-glaſſes</hi> ſuffering our hopes and ſpirits to riſe &amp; fall according to the <hi>tydings</hi> of good and bad ſucceſſes; that we ſhould not live upon <hi>diurnall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faith,</hi> or upon the ayre of newes and intelligence: But let our hopes be like the life of the ſaints that is <hi>hid with Chriſt in God:</hi> Let them have a ſurer foundation than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that baſe carnality can ſuggeſt: Let not our confidence like heavy <hi>Eli</hi> fall backward and break their necke upon the report of every defeate: Had <hi>Eli</hi> born up thorow that blaſt, he might have ſeen that the <hi>loſſe</hi> of the <hi>Arke,</hi> was in concluſion, the <hi>advantage</hi> of Iſrael; and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112329:25"/>that the Philiſtians were never ſo ſhamefully <hi>beaten</hi> as by that <hi>victory;</hi> for that very <hi>Arke</hi> when it was ſet up in the houſe of <hi>Dagon</hi> did <hi>conquer</hi> the Idol in his <hi>own</hi> Temple, for his head and both the palmes of his hands were cut off upon the threſhold, and only the ſtumpe of <hi>Dagon</hi> was left whole: Yea, and the Philiſtines them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were faine at laſt, as it were to <hi>bribe</hi> their <hi>priſoner</hi> with <hi>golden-Mice and Emrods,</hi> to be gone; and were forced to ſend the Arke home againe, with ſhame, and coſt enough.</p>
            <p>But there are many ſpecious arguments given, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of ſuch carnall diffidence. As</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> Firſt, Oh! But there is <hi>great oppoſition,</hi> many, mighty ſtubborn enemies there are againſt us?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> This is a <hi>good evidence</hi> that you are about a choyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of <hi>Church-worke.</hi> Shew me a <hi>Reformation</hi> (I thinke there is ſcarcely one) in the booke of God, or in our Proteſtant Hiſtories, that went on <hi>without diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties</hi> and obſtructions. So that theſe very <hi>crags</hi> and <hi>bogs</hi> which you paſſe thorow in the way, are not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, but <hi>way-markes,</hi> that is, certaine ſignes that you are right in the old Reformation-way that hath ever bin trodden. Thus <hi>Aſa</hi> had no ſooner ſet upon a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in <hi>Judah,</hi> (2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.) by <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting</hi> ſtrictly with God; by pulling downe Idolatry, and by removing Queen <hi>Maacha</hi> her Capuchins, but a thouſand thouſand <hi>Ethiopians</hi> are let in upon his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as though Hell it ſelfe had bin let looſe. So King <hi>Hezekiah, After theſ things</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>and the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of them,</hi> (2. Chron. 32.1.) that is, after <hi>three Chapters</hi> full of Reformation that you reade of before; <hi>Then Senacherib, King of Aſſyria, came and entered into Judah with a great Army.</hi> Therefore theſe bogs, crags,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112329:26"/>and brambles, are approved way-markes and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Againe, you muſt give <hi>parting-Devills</hi> leave to teare and ſome when they are to be immediatly caſt out. The evill ſpirit will have one <hi>pull</hi> with the poſſeſſed perſon, when he is packing. You know it is ſo ſaid, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.12. <hi>The Devill is come downe having great wrath, becauſe hee knowes that he hath but a ſhort time.</hi> And ſo in <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.26. When the <hi>dumbe Devill</hi> was to be caſt out (as how many dumbe Devils are now caſting out of many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes in the land!) hee did teare the man, and rent him ſore, that he was as one dead. This we muſt look for, it is a ſigne that the <hi>Devill is going.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> But the work is <hi>tedious,</hi> oh this <hi>prolixity</hi> is that which doth weary us?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſm. </seg>1</label> This is but <hi>proportionable,</hi> when a <hi>humour</hi> hath been ſo long a growing and cruſting in the Kingdom; it would be dangerous to <hi>purge</hi> it ſuddenly; our <hi>Body-Politique</hi> would hardly beare the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>Phyſick.</hi> This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity therefore is a wiſe mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Adde, that all this prolixity is <hi>uſuall</hi> in ſuch ſolide Church-work. The <hi>returne</hi> of the Jewes <hi>from Babylon,</hi> taking-in the whole of it, that is, the two pieces, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and temporall (the <hi>building</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and of the <hi>wall</hi> of the <hi>City</hi>) was upon the <hi>wheele,</hi> as I remember, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſome <hi>ſeven Princes</hi> reignes,
<note place="margin">Helvici Chronol.</note> 
               <hi>viz. Cyrus, Cambyſes, Darius Histaſpis, Xerxes</hi> or <hi>Ahaſuerus, Artaxerxes Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimanus, Darius Nothus, Artaxerxes Mnemon:</hi> But our <hi>Reformation</hi> as yet is but in the reigne of the <hi>ſixth King</hi> ſince it began; The <hi>number</hi> may be thus computed, King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. King <hi>Edward</hi> 6. Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>Iames,</hi> and our <hi>Soveraign</hi> that now reigneth. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>prolixity</hi> hath a <hi>patterne,</hi> 'tis uſuall.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:112329:26"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> Laſtly, it is alſo <hi>profitable</hi> and advantageous for us. It is true, when a <hi>River</hi> runneth with many turnings and windings, the <hi>veſſell</hi> that ſailes upon her doth make the <hi>longer</hi> voyage from place to place; but thoſe <hi>turnings</hi> and <hi>Meanders</hi> of the <hi>River</hi> are abundantly profitable to the bordering <hi>inhabitants,</hi> both to prevent <hi>inundations,</hi> by breaking the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>ſlouds,</hi> and to multiply rich <hi>Meadows</hi> and paſtures by its various indentures: So there is the <hi>leſſe danger,</hi> and the <hi>more fruitfulaeſſe</hi> by the <hi>prolixity</hi> of this myſterious work.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> But in the meane-while we are <hi>undone</hi> in our eſtates? </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> That was <hi>Micha's</hi> language when he had loſt his <hi>Idoll.</hi> Take heed that wee doe not <hi>idolize</hi> our eſtates and make them our gods, then indeed wee ſhall cry-out and ſay as he did, <hi>What have we more?</hi> But,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Farther, they are but <hi>exchanges</hi> of temporals for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals, earth for gold: hath not thy <hi>ſoule gained</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by theſe troubles in recompence of that which thy <hi>purſe</hi> hath <hi>loſt?</hi> What, not ſome experience, ſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, faith or holineſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> However, thy <hi>God is left</hi> with thee ſtill, and that God is able to fetch ſweet out of bitter, <hi>good</hi> out of <hi>evill,</hi> not onely out of the evill of <hi>puniſhment,</hi> but out of the evill of <hi>ſinne</hi> it ſelfe. In ſhort, this Doctrine doth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all carnall objections that can be moved, but I muſt haſten.</p>
            <p> Are Gods great ſalvations carried on in a myſtery? Then in the <hi>fourth place,</hi>
               <note n="4" place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 4. To Adviſe and Counſel.</note> let us be <hi>adviſed</hi> to looke upon this work <hi>as it is</hi> to be <hi>carried-on,</hi> that is, ſpiritually, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily, myſteriouſly; that ſo we may <hi>not</hi> be <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken</hi> in our way and taske, as many carnall <hi>politicians</hi> and formall <hi>Neuters</hi> have miſtaken the work, and ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaried and fallen away at laſt.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:112329:27"/>
            <p>Conſider, <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>Beloved,</hi> it is not a <hi>Iourney,</hi> but a <hi>Voyage,</hi> which the Lord hath put you upon: You know the difference; in a Voyage there is one and the ſame <hi>common ſafety</hi> or ſhip-wrack to all the paſſengers, they muſt ſwim or ſink together: Not ſo in a land Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: In a Voyage there is <hi>much hard-ſhip</hi> by lodging, dyet, ſtraightneſſe, and <hi>dangers</hi> by rockes, ſands, Pirats, tempeſts; Not ſo in a land-journey. But eſpecially I call your taske a Voyage, in reſpect of the <hi>vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous motions</hi> and <hi>path-leſſe wayes</hi> into which your worke doth carry you. Sometimes the Sea-man is forced to <hi>bord it</hi> to and fro, ſo that an unskilfull ſpectator would thinke that he doth go forth and backe: Another while he is faine to <hi>ſtrike all</hi> his <hi>ſailes,</hi> and to drive at <hi>Hull,</hi> ſo that he ſeemes utterly to neglect his <hi>Veſſell;</hi> yet all this while hee is at his worke, and doth make way as he can. But above all the reſt, you muſt remember that in a Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age there are <hi>no Lanes,</hi> no foot paths, no high-way <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curies</hi> to direct the Sea-men; all their directions muſt be fetched from the <hi>Pole</hi> and Stars compared with their Card, their <hi>Compaſſe,</hi> and touched <hi>Needle,</hi> their <hi>path</hi> lyeth <hi>in Heaven,</hi> not below. So you have <hi>a God above,</hi> a guide in Heaven, you have his <hi>Word and Will</hi> for your Card &amp; Compaſſe; and your own <hi>hearts touched with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you,</hi> ſtill ſtanding <hi>God-ward:</hi> Theſe muſt, theſe can guide you thorow a ſea of miſeries and myſteries unto the <hi>Haven</hi> of Reformation and deliverance where you would bee. Let theſe <hi>Guides</hi> and <hi>Guidances</hi> bee cloſely followed, and then <hi>no matter</hi> for waves and windes, no matter for <hi>Sea-ſickneſſe,</hi> 'tis a good <hi>ſigne</hi> of the progreſſe of the ſhip, and 'tis good <hi>Phyſicke</hi> to the paſſenger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Quest.</note> But ſuppoſe all the premiſſes are granted, namely that this work in its carriage is ſo ſpirituall, caſuall, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112329:27"/>tradictory, ſo truely <hi>myſterious;</hi> how then may we ſo order and leſſon our ſelves, as to diſcharge <hi>our duties</hi> in ſuch difficult ſervice? This myſtery doth ſeeme to leave us in a meere muſe of contemplation; what <hi>action</hi> or <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> is there left to us to be performed in this caſe? what doing leſſons may be fetched from hence?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> There are ſome ſure <hi>Practicall Leſſons</hi> to be learnt from the myſterious carriage of our preſent ſalvations; and that I may ſhew them the more fully, you muſt know that in this worke there are two parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aliquid Divinum, &amp;c.</hi> Something Divine, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, which is chiefly the <hi>Lords ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aliquid Humanum, &amp;c.</hi> Something more humane and ſecular, which is <hi>mans ends</hi> and aymes.</p>
            <p>Now the great leſſon in generall which we are to learne, is to <hi>ſticke</hi> and cleave to all <hi>Gods ends</hi> above any of our owne. It was a great errour of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai</hi> complaineth of it, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.2. that they fell a build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their <hi>owne houſes,</hi> but let the <hi>houſe of God</hi> lie waſt; therefore the Lord is faine to curſe, and <hi>croſſe</hi> them in their <hi>owne</hi> ſelviſh deſignes, even in <hi>the fruit of the field,</hi> and in their very meate, drinke, and cloth, as you may reade verſe 6. <hi>You have ſowne much, and bring in little, ye eate, and have not enough; yee drinke, but yee are not filled with drinke; yee cloth yee, but there is none warme, and he that earneth wages putteth it into a broken bag.</hi> God did croſſe them in things neereſt to them, that ſo they might looke more after <hi>his part</hi> of the worke. And indeed it is the wonderfull mercy of God to us, that theſe two parts of the worke (<hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Deliverance</hi>) are ſo <hi>twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted</hi> together, that we are not able to ſeparate them. God hath now ſo indiſſolubly interwoven the <hi>reforming of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> with the <hi>ſettlement of lawes and liberties,</hi> that we
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112329:28"/>cannot <hi>picke off</hi> the latter, and leave the former; Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (I feare) we ſhould ere this, have bin playing the children, that uſe to eate of their <hi>hony,</hi> and then throw the <hi>bread</hi> to the dogs. But our Father hath ſo wiſely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the whole, that if we will have no <hi>Reformation of Religion,</hi> we ſhall have no more <hi>Lawes, Parliaments, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> nor <hi>Priviledges;</hi> Therefore it will be our wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to looke chiefly after the <hi>Lords part</hi> of the worke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Quest.</note> But, What is Gods Part, End, or Aime?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> I anſwer, the Lords ends, <hi>deſignes,</hi> or defires, (as I may call them) in this great worke, may be conſidered two wayes; either <hi>generally,</hi> or <hi>particularly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> Firſt,
<note n="1" place="margin" type="runSum">Promote Gods gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſignes. Of Piety.</note> his <hi>generall,</hi> or publique <hi>deſignes</hi> which he doth owne and aime at, requiring us to promote them, may be reduced to theſe three ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Workes</hi> of <hi>Piety.</hi> The Lord doth abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Reformation of Religion at this time, both in <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> in the Church. We muſt out with Idols, not onely thoſe in wood, ſtone, or glaſſe, that is in walls and windowes; but thoſe living Idols that are in Pewes and in ſome Pulpits, they muſt out; I meane all <hi>Idoll-ſhepheards, and dumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dogs.</hi> cloſe with the handling of it <hi>teaching Prieſt, they were without Law:</hi> A <hi>Preacherleſſe</hi> people, wil be a <hi>lawleſſe</hi> people. In ſhort, the Lord would have you to demoliſh all <hi>high places,</hi> and not to leave ſo much as the <hi>ſtumpe of Dagon</hi> remaining: Yea to bury all the <hi>reliques</hi> of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh <hi>Jezabel,</hi> even the <hi>skull,</hi> and the <hi>feet,</hi> and the <hi>palmes of her hands.</hi> Alſo the Lord doth expect that you ſhould promote the late <hi>Solemne League &amp; Covenant,</hi> that <hi>triple Cable</hi> of the three Kingdomes, by which the <hi>Anchor</hi> of our hope is faſtned, that three-fold Cord that binds all
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112329:28"/>theſe Kingdomes together and unto God; and is like that golden chaine with which the <hi>Tyrians</hi> (when <hi>Alexander</hi> beleaguered them) bound faſt their <hi>tutelar</hi> god, <hi>Apollo;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Curtius in vitâ Alex.</note> for feare he would leave their City. Thus if yee do firſt build the <hi>Lords-houſe</hi> and do become faithfull <hi>Midwives</hi> to his labouring Church, then doubtleſſe will the Lord <hi>deale well with you, and will make you houſes,</hi> as Exod. 1.17.20.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of Iuſtice.</note> 
               <hi>Workes of Juſtice</hi> are a part of Gods generall deſign at this time, you cannot but remember the ſervice of <hi>Phinehas</hi> in executing of judgement when it was a ſad time with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the <hi>double reward</hi> that followed; <hi>publique</hi> to the State, (the plague was ſtaid,) and <hi>private</hi> to his own family, the ſervice of God in the Church was particularly intayled upon him and his poſterity. <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. And bleſſed be God, that you have now put in to the ſcales of Juſtice; the <hi>Archeſt Prelate</hi> of the land. Beleeve it, ſuch ſervices as theſe, are the way to procure unto us a <hi>valley of Achor</hi> for a doore of hope, even then when we do fly before the enemy, as <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.26. when <hi>Achan</hi> was found out and put to his <hi>tryall</hi> according to juſtice, the wrath of God was ſtopped; and the late vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious City of <hi>Ai</hi> is ſoone taken in.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord doth now call for <hi>workes</hi> and <hi>acts of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> too, that is,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Of Mercy.</note> that you take ſpeciall <hi>notice</hi> of the moſt <hi>doing</hi> and <hi>ſuffering places</hi> and perſons, that have layd out themſelves in this cauſe to the utmoſt, that like that poor <hi>widow,</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 17. have made a <hi>cake</hi> for the publique, out of their <hi>handfull</hi> of <hi>meale,</hi> and thereupon are much diſtreſſed and ſcanted. You remember what <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Abiathar,</hi> when for his <hi>ſake</hi> all the perſons of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe were ſlain by <hi>Saul, Abide thou with me, feare not, for he that ſeeketh my life, ſeeketh thy life, but with me
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112329:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:112329:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:112329:30"/>ſhalt thou be in ſafety:</hi> Much more ought thoſe faithfull Perſons, Towns, Cities, and Countries to be releeved that have been moſt active and paſſive for God and the Kingdome in this Cauſe.</p>
            <p>And here,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">A Digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Weſt.</note> Oh how gladly could I weepe in a <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> for, and over the <hi>Country</hi> of <hi>my Nativity,</hi> the <hi>place of my fathers Sepulchres which lyeth waſt,</hi> where ſo many houſes and places are <hi>conſumed with fire!</hi> Oh the unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld miſery of the ſtill-declining weſt! <hi>Is it nothing to you, all ye that paſſe by! Behold and ſee if there be any ſorrow like unto</hi> our <hi>ſorrow, which is done unto us, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted</hi> us, <hi>in the day of his fierce anger, Lamen.</hi> 1.12. Could I but <hi>draw</hi> forth in their due <hi>colours</hi> the <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> of thoſe parts of the <hi>Land,</hi> I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (what ever fame may chatter) that I ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with the <hi>dryeſt-heart</hi> in this great Aſſembly, to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute,</hi> at leaſt a <hi>teare</hi> towards our reliefe and ſuccour. True, I confeſſe the <hi>Lord is righteous, for we have rebelled againſt his mouth;</hi> but yet for <hi>doing</hi> and <hi>ſuffering</hi> in this great Cauſe, I am perſwaded thoſe parts may be ranked amongſt the <hi>foremoſt</hi> of the Kingdome: And my humble deſire is, that accordingly they may have <hi>place in your prayers and cares.</hi> Thus let the Lords <hi>generall</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique <hi>deſignes</hi> and <hi>ends</hi> be firſt conſidered and promoted.</p>
            <p> But ſecondly,
<note n="2" place="margin" type="runSum">Promote Gods parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes.</note> I muſt tell you that God hath other <hi>col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterall deſignes,</hi> (and as I may call them,) <hi>intermediate ends</hi> in this ſtrange worke, which we ought alſo to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and further to our uttermoſt; that's the ſecond <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall leſſon. As it is</hi> with thoſe that labour to finde out the <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loſophers-ſtone</hi> by diſtillations, their <hi>ultimate</hi> and principall end is to <hi>make gold,</hi> yet by the way and <hi>collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> they finde out many rare <hi>experiments</hi> and excellent chymicall extractions, which are of precious uſe and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112329:30"/>value: So is it in this great work of God, his <hi>grand</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall deſigne is publique ſalvation, both by Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Deliverance; but he hath many <hi>collaterall,</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionall, intermediate <hi>deſignes</hi> and effects which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth and produceth by the way. As for <hi>inſtance</hi> he hath (ſuppoſe) a <hi>deſign,</hi> and an experiment to be made upon his <hi>owne Church</hi> and people, as to <hi>try</hi> the particular graces of this or that ſaint, what ſtrength of <hi>faith,</hi> what depth of <hi>humility,</hi> what latitude of <hi>patience</hi> there is in their hearts: Or if not for tryall, then (ſuppoſe) for <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,</hi> or <hi>correcting,</hi> or <hi>improving;</hi> and it ſhould be our care to <hi>record</hi> ſuch experiments for after times, whether they tend to our humiliation, or to our conſolation. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother while the Lord hath a <hi>deſigne</hi> upon the <hi>enemy</hi> (as I ſhewed in my grounds) to make him fill up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſinne, and confuſion of face or perſon. The open adverſaries muſt have their <hi>full loade,</hi> and the ſecret Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters muſt be <hi>detected,</hi> as 'tis ſayd, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.35. <hi>Yea a ſword ſhal pierce through thine own ſide, that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed.</hi> The <hi>ſtabs</hi> and gaſhes of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſword do <hi>open</hi> and let out many a ſecret thought. <hi>Who ſo is wiſe, and will of ſerve theſe things, even they ſhall underſtand the loving kindneſſe of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 107.43.
<note n="5" place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe 5. Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let the <hi>cloſing branch</hi> of application bee a <hi>Cordiall.</hi> There is a Cordiall in this Doctrine, and I hope a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall is not unſeaſonable at a <hi>Fast,</hi> ſo as it enableth us the more heartily to go through the work of the day. Then here is a <hi>melting Cordiall,</hi> for by the <hi>myſterious carriage</hi> of our preſent worke we may eaſily gather that God is now upon ſome <hi>great ſalvation,</hi> yea upon a ſalvation <hi>from We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Babylon.</hi> The whole work in all its progreſſe looks exactly like the fore-told deſtruction of <hi>Babylon;</hi> For our God, even whilſt he <hi>hideth himſelf,</hi> is ſtill the <hi>Saviour
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112329:31"/>of this Iſrael.</hi> Mine encouragement therefore ſhall lye in the ſame words (for ſo God hath directed us) that you had in the <hi>morning</hi> from my <hi>reverend Brother;</hi> it ſeemes <hi>God</hi> wil have us <hi>both</hi> to drive the <hi>ſame naile,</hi> that it may be ſet home to the <hi>head.</hi> It is in <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Yet now be ſtrong, O Zerubbabel, ſaith the Lord, and be ſtrong O Joſuah, ſonne of Joſedech the high Priest, and be ſtrong O yee people of the Land and worke (for I am with you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.)</hi> Here is ſomething for <hi>all ranks,</hi> Parliament-men, <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbabel,</hi> Aſſembly of Divines, <hi>Ioſuah;</hi> And all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the whole Commonalty: The ſtrength of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lyeth in that ſweet <hi>Parentheſis</hi> at laſt, and I ſhall cloſe with the handlingof it <hi>(For I am with you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.)</hi> In which you may obſerve but theſe <hi>two blaſts</hi> to fill your ſailes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> who is the <hi>Master-builder,</hi> the Architect that imployes you, and accordingly you know whither to go for your <hi>wages. I am with you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Would any man aske a more honourable ſervice than under the <hi>Lord of Hoſts?</hi> For <hi>honor eſt in honorante,</hi> and it comes properly by Armes. Certainly, the Lord never put a more <hi>honourable imployment</hi> into the hands of the <hi>ſons of England,</hi> than he hath put this day into <hi>your hands.</hi> What, to be <hi>Champions</hi> for God, to be <hi>Builders, Factors, Reformers</hi> for the whole <hi>Protestant Cauſe</hi> and world! How many of our zealous <hi>Ancestors</hi> have caſt in their <hi>prayers, teares</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> to <hi>entaile</hi> upon us but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations and probabilities of this <hi>great work?</hi> How did they long to have ſeene one of theſe dayes a farre off, but did not ſee them? <hi>David</hi> was not permitted to build the <hi>Temple,</hi> but God reſerved that <hi>work</hi> for his ſon <hi>Iedidiah</hi> (for ſo the Lord himſelfe called <hi>Solomon)</hi> who was the <hi>beloved of the Lord.</hi> Do you think it a ſmall thing to be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112329:31"/>
               <hi>Gods Iedidiahs</hi> in this reſpect? To be builders of an <hi>Houſe</hi> to the <hi>God</hi> of heaven, is your honour. But that is but halfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> look upon <hi>Gods owning</hi> of the <hi>worke;</hi> This Lord of Hoſts <hi>will be with you.</hi> Would any man in the world deſire a <hi>clearer promiſe</hi> thnn was this to <hi>Zerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, I will be with you,</hi> upon my word, upon mine Honour, upon my Deity I will be with you?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> No (you will ſay) we would <hi>not wiſh</hi> a ſurer <hi>word</hi> to our ſelves, but that was made <hi>peculiarly</hi> to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> Had we but <hi>ſuch</hi> a promiſe, we would ſtick at nothing; Had we but the <hi>faith</hi> of heaven ſo ingaged to us?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> I anſwer, <hi>You</hi> have it <hi>as they</hi> had it, nay, in ſome ſort I may ſay, you have it <hi>more fully;</hi> For they had it promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and therefore it was <hi>in futuro,</hi> yet to come: But you have it, <hi>in praeſenti,</hi> in hand. Open your eyes and behold your incouragements; the Lord ſpeakes to you in <hi>deeds,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>Lo, I</hi> AM <hi>with you in all this worke; you may feele my preſence upon every occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> Let me <hi>reaſon</hi> with you a little before the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his <hi>providence</hi> over you.
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Conſider.</note>
               <note n="1" place="margin" type="runSum">Convention</note>
               <hi>Did ever</hi> the Lord ſo clearely, ſo viſibly <hi>owne</hi> an <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> as he hath owned you? Doe but <hi>first</hi> looke backe upon your firſt <hi>Convention.</hi> Are you not the very <hi>birth</hi> of the prayers of many generations? Were you, not as a <hi>brand ſnatched</hi> out of the fire kindled betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland?</hi> Juſt as were thoſe <hi>Reformers</hi> in the Babyloniſh Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; <hi>Is not this a brand</hi> (ſaith God, <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.2.) <hi>pluckt out of the fire? Suppoſe</hi> a man of judgement comming into a room where there is a fire burning, and he runneth haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the fire-ſide, <hi>ſnatcheth</hi> thence a piece of wood, and endevours by all meanes to extinguiſh the flame that is upon it; will not every rationall man preſently conclude
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112329:32"/>that he intendeth that piece for ſome <hi>ſpeciall ſervice?</hi> In this ſenſe (as I conceive) is that <hi>Metaphor</hi> uſed in that place; <hi>Is not this a brand pluckt out of the fire?</hi> As if the Lord ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Have I</hi> plucked <hi>Ioſuah</hi> out of the fire of Babylon, &amp; ſo this <hi>Parliament</hi> out of the fire of the two Kingdoms, when they were in a combuſtion ſome three years ſince, to caſt them into the conſuming flames againe at laſt? No ſurely, that is not the Lords uſuall manner.
<note n="2" place="margin" type="runSum">Continuance.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="3" place="margin" type="runSum">Supply.</note> And as for your <hi>Convention,</hi> ſo <hi>ſecondly</hi> conſider the progreſſe of providence in your <hi>ſettlement.</hi> How hath God faſtned you as <hi>a naile in a ſure place?</hi> This is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in which the Jewes did comfort themſelves at the time of their returne from <hi>Babylon, Ezra</hi> 9.8. <hi>And now for a little ſpace, grace hath been ſhewed from the Lord our God, to leave us a remnant to eſcape, and to give us a</hi> NAYLE <hi>in his holy place, &amp;c.</hi> Surely, you are our <hi>remnant eſcaped,</hi> without which we had been as <hi>Sodome,</hi> and as the inhabitants of <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> and you are faſtned as a <hi>nayle</hi> in a ſure place, by a <hi>ſpeciall Act</hi> for your continuance, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all former <hi>Parliaments.</hi> Well did the <hi>Lord fore-ſee</hi> both what a <hi>great worke</hi> himſelfe would put into your hands; and what <hi>great oppoſitions</hi> you ſhould meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, When God doth thus faſten a <hi>nayle</hi> of power and authority in a <hi>ſure place,</hi> hee doth uſually intend to hang ſome <hi>extraordinary weight</hi> and glory upon it, as it is ſaid of <hi>Eliakim,</hi> who was a figure of CHRIST, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 22.23. <hi>And I will fasten him as a nayle in a ſure place, &amp;c.</hi> verſ. 24. <hi>And they ſhall hang upon him all the glory of his Fathers Houſe, the off-ſpring and the iſſue, all veſſels (of ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie) from the veſſels of cuppes, even to all the veſſels of flaggons.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, beſides your extrordinary convention &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralleld
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112329:32"/>faſtning, Conſider laſtly what the Lord hath done <hi>for you</hi> and <hi>by you</hi> ſince you came together.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FOR YOU. How often hath he given a new life to <hi>your whole Houſe, collectively</hi> &amp; in common, &amp; that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by reſcuing you from bloody <hi>Aſſaſsinates?</hi> Oh! let the the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>January Anno</hi> 1641. be unto you as the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>November</hi> 1605. Sometimes by giving you the victory in the open field, when your lives lay at ſtake in the <hi>battle,</hi> as in both thoſe generall Battles at <hi>Keinton</hi> and <hi>Newbery.</hi> Beſides, how many of your <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers diſtributively</hi> have had their lives given unto them as a particular prey, being ſnactht out of naturall and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent deaths ſince they began this ſervice? I do not ſpeak this that your hearts ſhould be <hi>lifted up within you,</hi> but that they may be lifted up in the <hi>wayes</hi> of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next conſider what God hath done BY You alſo; did ever the Lord do <hi>ſo much work</hi> of this kind in ſo ſhort a time (how ever we thinke the time to be long) ſince Proteſtant Reformation began in the Chriſtian world?
<note place="margin">Sleidani Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria.</note> If ſo, then I was miſtaken or forgetfull in reading that exact <hi>Record</hi> of <hi>Reformation</hi> ſince <hi>Luthers</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>So much</hi> worke done (you will ſay?) Alas, alas, <hi>what is</hi> there <hi>done</hi> all this while, beſides the kindling of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall warre? As for Reformation there is <hi>nothing</hi> compleatly <hi>perfected</hi> in that to this day, for want of the <hi>Royall aſſent &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer firſt, yes there is ſomewhat already done, the beſt, the <hi>ſpirituall part</hi> of the worke doth ſtill go on, and the reaſon why we ſee it not, is becauſe we <hi>looke</hi> to the politique and outward part of the buſineſſe, more then
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112329:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:112329:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:112329:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:112329:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:112329:35"/>to the inward and ſpirituall part: For <hi>this</hi> abundantly goes on ſtill even in the middeſt of all the ſtormes; The <hi>Wall</hi> is <hi>building</hi> though in <hi>troublous times,</hi> as <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.25. Have you ever been upon the ſhore at low-water, and there obſerved the <hi>comming in</hi> of the <hi>tide;</hi> you ſhall ſee firſt one little wave creeping forwards, and preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring it ſelfe again, and ſo another and another, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one doth ſtill retreat as ſoone, as faſt, as it did advance, ſo that a diligent obſerver viewing the water in motion, may eaſily beleeve that the floud doth <hi>not</hi> at all <hi>increaſe.</hi> But <hi>ſet a marke,</hi> or keepe your ſtanding neere the waſh of the waves, for a ſhort time, and then you ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clearly ſee and feele that all this while it is <hi>flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water,</hi> and anon inſenſibly it will be <hi>full-ſea.</hi> So in the preſent great worke, though there appears to be a <hi>viciſsitude</hi> of victories betwixt God and his enemies, though <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> doth ſeeme to a carnall eye <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> to go and come, yet ſtand ſtill a while and looke upon the ſpirituall, the religious part of the worke, and you ſhall find the <hi>waters</hi> of the ſanctuary ſtill flowing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, as in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> viſion, Chap. 47. firſt they were to the <hi>ancles,</hi> next to the <hi>knees,</hi> then to the <hi>loynes,</hi> and laſtly they were a <hi>River</hi> that could not be paſſed over. I meane that the <hi>worke of Reformation</hi> ſtill goes on; there we do get ground, as to <hi>perfect</hi> a Proteſtation into a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> to <hi>ripen</hi> an Impeachment into a <hi>Roote &amp; Branch,</hi> and in a word, to ſettle an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines</hi> as a generall <hi>reſiners fire</hi> to try all metals in the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> But ſecondly, whereas you ſay, that nothing is yet <hi>compleatly perfected</hi> for want of the <hi>Royall aſſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know this, that the Lord doth carry-on this frame of building in like manner as <hi>Solomons Temple</hi> was built. Doe you not remember how <hi>Solomon</hi> built his Temple?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112329:35"/>you may ſee it in 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 6.7. <hi>And the houſe when it was in building was built of ſtone, made ready before it was brought thither, ſo that there was neither hammer or axe, or any toole of iron heard in the houſe while it was in building:</hi> And in <hi>King</hi> 5.6. it is ſaid that the <hi>Cedar-trees</hi> were <hi>hewen</hi> and made fit in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and then they were <hi>brought</hi> downe by water unto the place where they were to be uſed: and verſe 15. you ſhall reade that <hi>Solomon had threeſcore and ten thouſand that bare burthens, and fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcore thouſand that were hewers in the Mountaines &amp;c.</hi> Juſt ſo is the building of this Chriſtian Proteſtant Temple carryed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The Lord prepareth <hi>one piece</hi> of the building in <hi>Germany,</hi> there he hath had thouſands of <hi>hewers</hi> of wood and fellers of trees theſe twenty yeers, to cut down ſome and to ſquare-out others for this ſtructure; he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that beare <hi>burthens</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and they ſhall bring in another kinde of materials; And then <hi>Scotland</hi> doth come in perhaps with <hi>ſoader</hi> and <hi>cement,</hi> they ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther us in <hi>Covenanting;</hi> and at laſt, when all theſe mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials ſhal be brought in place <hi>by water</hi> (by our prayers) then you ſhall ſee a glorious Temple ſet up, perhaps in one weeke, nay, in a day or a night, and that without the <hi>noyſe of axe or hammer, or any toole of iron:</hi> You are <hi>hewing</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Parliament;</hi> the <hi>Divines</hi> are <hi>ſquaring</hi> in their <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> in one night the Lord is able to worke upon the <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> (for he hath it in his hand) and to deliver him into the boſome of you his faithfull Counſell, &amp; then the whole work may ſuddenly be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and finiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Onward</hi> therefore <hi>Noble Builders,</hi> onward, <hi>up and be doing</hi> your ſeverall parts; your <hi>God</hi> is invincible; your <hi>Cauſe</hi> is invincible, and nothing is ſo like to hazard us as <hi>not adventuring:</hi> Your labour, your coſt, your adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, cannot be <hi>in vaine,</hi> in the Lord. Oh remember that counſell in <hi>Peter,</hi> it is uſed there in a ſpirituall way;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112329:36"/>I ſhall borrow it in this ſenſe, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hope unto the end,</hi> that is, adventure for God and truſt him to the <hi>uttermoſt,</hi> to the <hi>brinke,</hi> to the <hi>edge,</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> of all meanes and poſſibilities, to the <hi>laſt inch</hi> of the candle, to the <hi>laſt duſt</hi> of <hi>meale</hi> in the barrell, to the <hi>leaſt drop of oyle</hi> in the bottome of the Cruze. Thus did that poore widow. Thus did <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 22. Firſt his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and himſelfe went, verſe 8. to the <hi>mount,</hi> he built an <hi>Altar,</hi> layd the <hi>wood</hi> in order, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound Iſaac</hi> his ſon, <hi>layd</hi> him on the Altar upon the wood (yet the tryall is not come to the edge, the brinke, the uttermoſt:) But laſtly, verſe 10. <hi>Abraham ſtretched forth his</hi> hand, and tooke the <hi>knife</hi> to ſlay his ſonne. This indeed was <hi>hope againſt hope,</hi> as, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18. This was truſting <hi>to the end.</hi> But was <hi>Abraham</hi> a <hi>loſer</hi> by it? Sure I am that King <hi>Saul</hi> did loſe a kingdom for want of an <hi>houres faith,</hi> and adventuring farther, as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to truſt the Lord to the uttermoſt end of meanes, yea above, and againſt them, rather then ſin againſt him by unbelife. Labour (in three words) to play the <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> the <hi>Davids,</hi> the <hi>Samſons</hi> in this worke.</p>
            <p>Firſt to play the <hi>Solomons:</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> that is, as you have begun this <hi>Reformation,</hi> ſo do your utmoſt endeavour to <hi>finiſh</hi> it in your dayes. Beleeve it, when you have built the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> you ſhall have both leave and ability to build your <hi>owne houſes.</hi> You read ſo of <hi>Solomon</hi> in 1. <hi>King</hi> 7.1. When he had built the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> then he built his <hi>owne houſe,</hi> and a houſe for his <hi>Wife,</hi> and the houſe of the Foreſt of <hi>Lebanon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if you may not bee the <hi>Solomons,</hi> yet labour to be
<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Davids</note> yet labour to be <hi>Davids</hi> in this <hi>worke,</hi> You know God denied unto <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> the honour of building his <hi>Temple:</hi> Yet <hi>David</hi> would not utterly bee put of; hee will bee <hi>doing</hi> as much as he may: Firſt <hi>himſelfe offereth</hi> to the <hi>worke,</hi> 1 Chron. 29. hee offereth <hi>Gold, Silver, Braſſe, Iron, Wood, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:112329:36"/>Next, hee <hi>drawes-in</hi> his <hi>Nobles</hi> and all his <hi>People,</hi> as deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as hee can. And thirdly, hee <hi>leaveth</hi> alſo a <hi>Stocke</hi> of <hi>Prayers</hi> behind him, 2 Chron. 29.10. Yea, finally he gives a <hi>charge</hi> unto his ſonne <hi>Solomon</hi> to goe thorough with the <hi>worke,</hi> 2 Chron. 28.11. And leaves him a <hi>patterne</hi> of the Houſe: And even thoſe very prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and purpoſes of <hi>David</hi> were richly <hi>rewarded,</hi> 2 Sam. 7.4. Thus if the Lord for our ſinnes and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe hath decreed that your <hi>carcaeſſs</hi> and ours ſhall <hi>fall</hi> in the wilderneſſe, and that wee ſhall onely ſee this <hi>Canaan</hi> afarre off; yet let theſe <hi>two leſſons</hi> be learned. 1. Let every ſoule bee carefull to <hi>avoyd</hi> all thoſe <hi>ſinnes</hi> that are wont to draw downe this puniſhment of <hi>not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entring;</hi> See ſome of them, 1 Cor. 10.6, 7, &amp;c. <hi>Beware of lusting, of idolatry, of tempting of God, of murmuring, &amp;c.</hi> 2. Let us labour to contribute and <hi>ſtore up</hi> materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls for thoſe that ſhall finiſh the worke after us.</p>
            <p>And laſtly,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">The Samſons</note> if you may not bee permitted to doe ſo much as <hi>Solomon,</hi> or as <hi>David,</hi> yet at laſt, at leaſt let us endeavour to play the <hi>Samſons</hi> in this <hi>worke.</hi> What is that? You ſhall reade it, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.29. When <hi>Samſon</hi> could not conquer the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> could not make a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough <hi>ſalvation</hi> of it, as he deſired, yet the text ſaith, <hi>He called unto the Lord, and ſaid, Remember me I pray thee, and ſtrengthen me I pray thee onely this once, that I may be at once avenged of the Philiſtines for my two eyes: And Samſon tooke hold of the two middle pillars, upon which the houſe ſtood, and on which it was borne up,</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>Let mee die with the Philiſtins: and he bowed himſelf with all his might, and the houſe fell upon all the people that were therein; ſo the dead which he ſlew at his death, were more than thoſe which he ſlew in his life.</hi> My meaning is this; <hi>Better</hi> for us if we cannot out-live <hi>Antichrist,</hi> out-live <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the enemies of <hi>Reformation;</hi> to adventure (as far as wee are warranted) our ſelves to death in the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> yea, Let us
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112329:37"/>
               <hi>take hold</hi> of the <hi>pillars</hi> of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Dagon,</hi> of the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Now let me die with Antichriſt, Rome</hi> and <hi>Babylon;</hi> Better ſo (I ſay) than to live with the <hi>eyes</hi> of our <hi>Religion</hi> put out, and to <hi>grind</hi> in the <hi>mill</hi> of <hi>ſlavery:</hi> For by this meanes the <hi>children</hi> that ſhall come after us ſhall ſit upon our tombes and ſay, that they had active parents, which with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r bloud and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes did dreſſe the ground for Reformation to ſpring up after them. For mine owne <hi>part,</hi> I ſhall ſay, he that is of ſo baſe a ſpirit that can be content to <hi>out-live</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſme and Parliaments, let it be his <hi>puniſhment</hi> to out-live them. I deſire not to fall under the juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of an heathen,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vitae est avidus quiſquis non vult,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mando ſecum pereunte mori.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To ſhut up all. <hi>Be ſtrong in the Lord and in the power of his might;</hi> upon the eternall and infinite <hi>faith</hi> of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and in the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Iehovah,</hi> your loſſes for his ſake ſhall be repaid. Will you take that word? Then there are <hi>two</hi> ſpeciall <hi>promiſes</hi> which I will commend unto you in the cloſe of all; Oh that they were <hi>Written</hi> over the <hi>doores</hi> of the <hi>Houſes</hi> of Parliament!</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.29.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Every one that hath forſaken houſes, or bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or ſiſter, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, orlands</hi> (can you reckon up any thing elſe?) <hi>for my names ſake, he ſhall receive an hundred fold;</hi> (God will pay him the very intereſt) <hi>and</hi> he <hi>ſhall inherit everlaſting life</hi> (to boote.)</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. v. 35.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Whoſoever will ſave his life ſhall loſe it, but he that loſeth his life for my ſake ſhall find it.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe places do <hi>deceive</hi> an <hi>active beleever</hi> at laſt; then let it be written upon my grave;</p>
            <p>
               <q>HERE LYETH THAT MINISTER THAT WAS MISTAKEN IN HIS GOD AND GOSPELL.</q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
